I wanted to do one about this problem I've been encountering.
Which I've been calling, not my problemism.
I've been thinking about this a lot
since I gave
a talk a while ago at a fancy advertising agency in London.
I think somebody dropped out of the panel last minute,
and they called me up. Can you step in?
So I went to this kind of, like, fancy advertising event.
It's quite a lot of people there,
maybe like a few hundred people there. I was talking on a panel.
And I did like
what I usually do, which is basically say,
listen, the economy is going to go
absolutely to sh*t, like it's already doing that.
And like if we don't take action to stop it,
it's going to get worse and worse and worse
and it's going to be absolutely f**king disaster.
And there was a lady on the panel,
by all accounts, quite a nice lady.
There's nothing against her personally.
But she, sort of, came in and said, well, you know, if,
if it all goes to sh*t like that, I would just,
I would just move to France, I’d move to Spain,
you know, I was like, alright, fine.
And then another guy on the panel
came in and he said, Well,
what gives me hope
is that, you know, if you look at the big picture,
you can look at the long term, look at nature.
What you see is that things move in cycles.
Things get better and things get worse,
things go up and things go down.
I remember thinking, Alright, that's good for you.
And what I couldn't help
but feel in this situation is basically, you know,
you're in this room full of
relatively well-paid people
who are doing pretty well for themselves, telling themselves
and telling each other, okay, yeah,
well, worlds going to happen to this sh*t. But
it's alright because things move in cycles.
You know what I mean!
and I felt like, okay.
What I saw here in this space was basically
a lot of people,
they're probably not all very wealthy people,
but they've got decent, well-paid jobs at the moment
and they're working hard and
they want to believe
that things will get better without their intervention
because they don't want to have to f**king
do anything, basically.
And this is what I've been calling, not my problemism.
And what you've got here
in this conversation is basically two kinds of different
not my problemism.
One of which is like,
okay, things are going to sh*t but it’s okay because I’ll leave.
And the other one is okay, things are going to sh*t.
But you know, big picture, things
move in cycles, it’s out of my control and
it's understandable, right?
Like, it's
not easy
to live in a world where things are getting worse
as quickly as they are
and where it's kind of increasingly obvious
that things are going to get really, really bad, right?
And I think personally
that I have a responsibility
to try and do something to stop that.
But, you know, as an individual, we don't have a lot of power
and it's much easier to just focus on our own
things like trying to get better job, trying to make more money.
You know,
I've got to renovate my kitchen,
you know what I mean, I'm
trying to find the new yoga club, or whatever.
Life is full of little things that we would rather focus on
than trying to stop this big thing that is out of our control.
And, you
know, another thing that I hear, especially when I talk to guys
who I use to work with in banking,
and these are pretty rich guys. It's not my job.
It's the job of the politicians.
It's not my job, it’s the job of the politicians, alright.
The message I want to send is.
I can absolutely guarantee you
the politicians are not going to f**king fix this.
The people whose job
it is to fix this, I guarantee you they're not going to fix it.
You know, I spoken to a lot of them.
These guys, they don't understand it.
They're not going to fix it.
But more than that, they're not f**king getting hurt by it
from where they're sitting, things look pretty fine.
You know, these well paid advertising execs, these bankers,
these politicians, you know,
especially top level politicians, you know, Rishi Sunaks,
who have £700 million, you know,
I mean, these sort of politicians,
they're not all that wealthy,
but they become wealthy very quickly.
They're not going to fix it.
I guarantee you they're not going to fix it.
So we live in a world where the people
whose problem it definitely should be,
top level politicians, top level economists, top level bankers,
100% guarantee they're not going to fix it.
So whose problem is it and whose responsibility is it to fix it?
And this is the reason why
I stopped doing articles for the Guardian and moved to YouTube.
Because if I wrote articles for The Guardian,
I could talk to politicians in the Labour Party.
I could talk to economists at think thanks.
These guys are not getting it.
They're not going to fix it,
even though it might be their responsibility to fix it.
They're not going to fix it.
The people who are getting hit
are literally the ordinary men and women out there
doing anything, working as teachers, working
as hairdressers, working as taxi drivers,
working as electricians, working in offices.
These regular people are the guys who are going to get hit.
And if you were to ask them,
whose job is it to prevent this economic disaster,
they don't think it's their job, right.
And it shouldn't be their job.
But the people whose job it is to fix this,
they're not going to fix it.
They are not going to fix this
because they don't think they're getting hurt by it.
So then this is not a moral question, right?
Like if my house is burning down
and I know the firefighters are not going to come fix it,
but it's my f**king job to get the family out of the house.
You know, so I'm turning around, the reason I moved to YouTube
is because the way I see it,
I know these guys are not economists,
and I know these guys are not firefighters,
but these are the guys whose house is burning down.
So
the way I see it, in a sense, this is not my problemism
is a big, is one of our biggest problems in a sense.
Because the situation that we have
is a situation in which 70, 80,
90% of people are going to be really,
really badly hit in the long term.
If it's not you, it's your kids, your grandkids.
I guarantee that. And I don't just say that I'll bet on this.
I bet on this every day,
and I make a ton of money doing it, right.
And people who don't believe that can go back
and look at my predictions from the beginning of COVID, right.
These guys are not going to fix it for you, right.
And you are going to get hit.
So you are the one who has to stop it.
And that means we are in a kind of perverse situation
where the responsibility that should be falling on
Oxford economics professors
and should be falling on top level politicians and top level
journalists is actually falling on
just regular people on the street
and they're not being given the support.
So there's a couple of messages I would like to send.
One, if you are a wealthy person
and you think it's not your problem,
ask yourself whose problem is, you know,
and ask yourself how you would feel
if it was your family on the line,
because in the long run it will be.
But really, the more important message
I want to send this to the average people
who are not from the elites of society.
The message I want to send to them is,
these guys at the top will not protect you,
but you can protect yourselves
by the only power that you have is strength in numbers.
And the only way you use your strength in numbers
is if enough ordinary people abandon Their not my problemism
and accept that it is our problem communally.
So I mean, this is a difficult thing
to achieve in an individualised society.
But the more I sit and think about this,
the more I realise the only defence ordinary people have
is that there's a lot of them.
And if they continue to act
in ways that are individualised
and refuse to accept that it is their collective problem,
the more power they will lose over time.
So, yeah, I wanted to share this story
and again, it's another concerning story, but
I believe that
ordinary people have the power to defend themselves,
but only if they come together and only if they understand.
So I'll keep doing what I do.
Explaining to people that the long run
situation is very bad if we don't act
and hopefully we'll be able to build a movement behind us here
where enough people come together and make things better.
So that's it, thank you.