Okay.
Welcome back to Garys Economics
for this special short video.
I know I am supposed to be on holiday.
I am unfortunately not on holiday just at the
moment and I'm finally allowed to tell you why.
Because I have been given permission to announce
that I am filming a documentary with Channel 4,
about inequality and money and the
financial situation of young people and how to
get rich and wealth taxes and all this stuff.
And that's going to come
out at some point next year.
I'm working on it now.
This is primarily one of the reasons why I've had
to pause the YouTube and Instagram and such things.
So I'm announcing that now.
And we also want to talk a little bit about
people we would like to speak to.
So I'm going to be interviewing a lot of
people and there are a few groups of people
that we would really like to speak to
that we'd love to get your help getting.
One of which is the famous millionaires
who are fleeing the country because they are
terrified of the imminent wealth taxes, despite
the fact that there aren't any wealth taxes.
You might have heard a lot of stories in
the news that lots of millionaires are leaving
because they're really scared of me tearing
the country apart and taxing rich people.
If you or anyone you know is a millionaire who
is leaving the country or thinking of leaving the
country or threatening to leave the country because
you are worried about wealth taxes, get in touch.
Let us know.
The email for the documentary is
garyfilm@mindhouse.co.uk
That's the production
company making the documentary.
garyfilm@mindhouse.co.uk
We would love to speak to millionaires
who are so terrified of me that
they are going to leave the country.
We would also like to speak to senior politicians
in Labour, especially anyone in the Treasury.
So come on, Rachel Reeves,
Darren Jones, Torsten Bell.
You know who you are.
Come here to my wonderful kitchen table and talk to
us about why you are not bringing in wealth taxes.
And lastly, is there anyone who
you think that we should talk to?
Anyone you would love to see on the documentary?
If there is, let us know.
garyfilm@mindhouse.co.uk or
suggest names in the comments.
So that's it.
That's why I am on holiday.
Unfortunately, I'm not on holiday.
I'm filming a documentary with Channel 4.
I'd love to be on holiday.
Hopefully one day I will be,
but we'll do that once this is finished.
So that's it.
We'll keep you in touch when
the documentary's coming out.
Otherwise, let us know, millionaires
who are leaving the country or anyone
you think we should definitely talk to.
Thank you.
Tax wealth, not work.