okay welcome back to Gary's Economics
today is unfortunately my goodbye video for now
because this will be the last video in the 24/25
season, thank you
Okay so this is it
the last video while I go away
if you watch this I'll probably already be in Italy
I wanted to just talk
I've got here written on my script
just run with no script, but I can't to be honest
I'm absolutely knackered
I wanna talk a little bit about this season
and this season has been, I would say
probably the hardest season for me personally
of Gary's Economics if I'm honest
I think I probably exhausted myself a little bit
in the first half of the year
it seems ages ago now but the paperback came out in
end of January
and the first half of the year was absolutely insane
for me, it was absolutely crazy
I was everywhere
it felt like I couldn't live my life really
we were getting like 50 million views a month
it really felt like we were gonna take the world over
and I was working crazy crazy
crazy crazy hard and really
really really
really hard
I didn't realise it was gonna go on as long as it did
it just kept going and going and going
and I had a holiday planned in the spring
which I kept postponing and postponing and postponing
and the holiday ended up being quite short
and I ended up working half the holiday
doing interviews all over the place
and then when I came back in June to start this season
it really felt like we were kind of
on the edge of winning wealth taxes
and I really wanted to like
hit the ground running and really go
and I started making videos in June
and it was probably only about 3, 4
videos in, I just started feeling like I was exhausted
to be honest
and I don't know if it's just me getting old
or if I worked too hard but it was
it was difficult for me because
we'd achieved so much and we'd come so close
it really felt like what it needed was for me to like
keep pushing and push more and more and more
it just felt like, the sort of the legs weren't there
I didn't have the energy I needed to really run in
it felt like when I'm really doing a lot of work
you know, I can be doing interviews
and doing these videos and writing articles
and appearing on people's podcasts
and it really feels like you can kind of
carry the thing on your back
but I couldn't really
This is the first time really
that I've ever done this channel
that I just felt like I didn't have
the energy that I needed
to push us to where we needed to be
and that was difficult for me
to be honest, especially
because
it felt like we were quite close to winning at times
but I think if I'm honest
we were probably never that close yet
and it's probably partially wishful thinking for me
anyway because when you're working so so
so hard you just wanna get there, right?
You wanna get there, you wanna reach the end
you wanna win and have it won and kind of go away
go on holiday for like a year
but the truth is, it was never gonna be that easy
we've made unbelievable, amazing
amazing strides this year to win the public
but what we've seen is
it's not enough just to win the public
you do need to figure out
how to win over the politicians
how to win over, you know
the media to some degree and this intellectual class
how do we break in to that sort of
how do we break in with the posh people, basically
and I think the truth is
we were never gonna quite make it this year
which is a shame, but the truth is
it's exactly what I predicted
you know, if you go and
if you go and look at the videos that we did
just before the election
this is exactly what I said would happen
it's exactly what I said Labour would do
there's not a single thing that's happened
that surprised me. I didn't expect Labour to come
over, and they haven't
I expected Labour to be unpopular and they have
I expected Labour to change leader
and it looks like they will
a new leader will come in
it's new opportunity but if I'm totally honest
I don't think we'll get them either
but we are in a much much
much stronger position than we were one year ago
two years ago three years ago
the size of this movement is huge now so
I'm gonna keep fighting.
So that was kind of where I was
when I came back and did the videos
I felt that my energy was kind of going
which is a shame
because I'd only been back a month,
month and a half and I always feel with these videos
I try my best to do them without a script
but it's hard when I'm tired
and I feel like when you go without a script
what really drives the videos
is your understanding and your passion and your energy
and it's sometimes difficult to combine those things
cause you wanna
keep that shape and structure and clarity
you get from understanding
but also allow that sort of passion to come through
and what I felt really during this season was
the energy was kind of going
and then we saw this like, massive
massive rise in the media salience of immigrant
refugee stuff, far right stuff
and that was really difficult for me
to be honest because
you know
I've always had this idea that I'm an economist
and I talk about the economy
and our current economic situation is not working
or not gonna work for 80, 90% of people
so we can really rally and unite the public on this
and a big part of
sort of, the philosophy of this channel
and my philosophy
is basically about uniting the public
and as this anti immigrant rhetoric really went up
and up and up
and up and up what I probably felt most personally
was just the division
basically, the division in the country
the division in the public, and for me it was difficult
you know, I know people think I'm a communist
I don't come from a political background
I come from a very working class, poor background
but then I've been to fancy universities
and I've worked fancy jobs
so now in many ways
I'm in a more sort of middle class space
and what I felt with this anti immigrant thing
reminded me a lot of how I felt with the Brexit thing
which was
I saw the sort of class divisions in this society
really being sort of torn at the seams
and it kind of felt like this division
between the world that I came from
and the world that I'm in now
and it's hard really, it's hard
it's sort of
it breaks my heart in a way to see so much division
and I worry. I worry that if
we don't do anything about this
we can end up kind of
going the way that America has gone
where basically the country is like split into two
and everybody with the red hat
hates everyone with the blue hat
and everyone with the blue hat
hates everyone with the red hat
and I don't want it to go that way
I don't want it to go that way
so I decided to speak a little bit more about
the protest and the migrant stuff
which is not something I'm super
super comfortable speaking about
but it felt like something I had to do
and I did my best to speak about it in a way that
is compassionate and understand what's happening
and I hope I said the right things
I do my best
but we've got to the end of the season now
I've been pushing it if I'm honest
trying to sort of push myself to keep going
because I was only away last
in May, June
and I felt bad to take another break
but I could feel that exhaustion coming
and when I get to the end of a season
I kind of
I kind of feel the same at the end of every season
which is this sense of
having really worked a lot
I put a lot of effort
into the this channel and these videos
and each season we achieve more
and each season we achieve more and
this year in particular
I think it's amazing what we've achieved
and you put so much work in
and you get to the end
and you realize that we still haven't won
and we're not even winning
and it's hard I think, I find that hard
but what I wanna say is, we are getting there
we are moving forward
the channel is like so
so much louder and bigger than it was
when I started this channel 5 years ago
I mean when I started 5 years ago
with my mate Simran
I never
ever would have imagined we could be what we are now
which is genuinely, legitimately
I think a major political player in this country
that's what we are and that growth is thanks to you
This channel is is ultimately a political experiment
which is to see whether
an almost unfunded YouTube channel can compete
with the major newspapers
and political broadcasters
TV channels, radio channels
on the basis of word of mouth from the public
just by being honest, being clear
being knowledgeable
and explaining what's happening to the public
and we're doing it, we're doing it
we're one of the major political players in the country
and I'll keep doing it, if we keep growing
we'll still be there
there's big opportunities next year
and I'll be back, I'll do my best to take ‘em
I wanna thank Jack, cameraman
Jack does great work
These videos are a lot tighter
when they go out than when I do them
and that's thanks to Jack's work
I never check his work
cause I have a implicit trust in him
he's doing a great job.
I wanna thank Oscar
he's the only employee on this channel
and he has asked me
he basically runs runs all the
all the background stuff, all the organizational stuff
and he has asked me in particular
in typically selfless Oscar fashion
to publicise
the merch that he's worked hard to get made
these tax wealth not work t shirts
I think there's more, we've got stickers
hoodies, tote bags...
Oscar's doing fantastic work
We'll put a comment in the link
a comment in the links...
a link in the comments for people who want to buy merch
I wanna say a very special
thank you to the patreon supporters
it's the patron supporters that pay Jack, that pay Oscar
we have never ever put any adverts in these videos
and the reason we're able to do that
is because of the Patreon supporters
it all works because of you
but more than anything like
it means a lot to me to see that
ordinary people are willing
to pay to support something they don't
get anything back for it
they pay because they care about this project
like I do, and when times are tough
it makes me feel like I'm not doing it alone
so yeah massive thanks to Jack, to Oscar
to all the patreon supporters
really appreciate that
I've got a long list of thanks here
I wanna thank other people who do this work
Gabriel Zucman doing amazing work in France
all the great guys at Patriotic Millionaires UK
especially Rebecca Gowland
fantastic work they do over there
I want to thank Zack Polanski for the massive work
he's done publicising wealth taxes
whether you like him or not
you know, I don't agree with him on everything
this guy has been doing so much work
publicising wealth taxes
we have to thank him. So many interviews
you gotta respect that
I've got a long list here of all the other creators
who I wanna thank. When I went away in May
I did a call out to people, to make art
to make, especially to make videos and there's so many
I'm gonna forget some. Jimmy the Giant as always
big friend of the channel
working his tits off doing great work
Frankie
Meditations of an Anxious Mind doing some great stuff
good lad, Forest Jar on Instagram
I think Forest Jar’s videos are really
really, really good work
go check them out
Anna Bocca, she's doing great work on YouTube
check out her channel. Barry's Economics
you gotta mention Barry's Economics
Barry's Economics, fantastic
I think he's nearly 10,000 subs
go check him out. Louisa Munch Critical Theory
these last two, Barry's Economics and Louisa Munch
I wanna give them a special mention
because I think the two of these made their channels
basically in response to the call out I did in May
saying I wanna see more people doing like, creating
So that means a lot to me
it's hard making a channel
you do a lot of work for not a lot of money
for basically no money for a lot of time
and I know how much work it is because I do it
so I really do appreciate you guys who
who are doing the work
Barry's Economics and Louisa Munch Critical Theory
the guys at Novara, Unlearning Economics
Punters Politics in Australia
Chloe Swarbrick in New Zealand
Ha-Joon Chang, doesn't have a channel
but I want him to make an Instagram about food
come on Ha-Joon Chang, you'll be really popular
I really appreciate other people doing it
I always feel guilty going on holiday
because I feel like I carry a lot of this movement
but I see more and more people making great videos
and it makes me feel like I can take breaks
which I need and I really appreciate that.
All of the other creatives who've,
people who sent us music, paintings
Jordan Stevens of Rizzle Kicks
putting us on the album
all of the grime artists who've been reaching out to us
Bashy, Toddla T everyone
the people who've been making t shirts, posters
stickers
it means a lot to me
this season's been a difficult one for me
I've worked so hard this year
and I've really exhausted myself
it's difficult doing creative work
when you feel exhausted I think the biggest
challenge about this particular part of the season is
in previous seasons
I've been very much focused on doing the creative work
doing the videos, doing the interviews
but this last season
I've been doing tons of work behind the scenes
which is trying to talk to think tanks
trying to talk to politicians
trying like, set stuff up
trying like, find ways to actually break into politics
and I hate it, I'm so bad at that
at that work
and it's so much easier to just be making the videos
trying to make amazing videos
and I'm not great at sort of multitasking
but we have to do it, we have to figure out ways this
This channel was
never about just making me famous on YouTube
supposed to be about changing policy
I'll keep doing that and
I wanna thank everyone who
who watches the videos who shares the videos
I really
really appreciate it. There's a
I live in East London and there's a
there's a famous mural down the street from me
called Cable Street Mural
which is, it's a mural from the
I guess it was maybe the 30s, back when
like serious fascism was on the rise
and Nazism was on the rise in Europe
and there was a big like, fascist Nazi movement here in
London and in the UK and there was a march
the fascist march in London
and the locals in east London came out
and they didn't accept it
there was a massive fight
there's a big mural down the street
which is nice if you're ever in London
go check it out. And I go
I cycle past it all the time and quite often
I'll stop and just have a little look
and I stopped the other day
and I was standing by this mural
and I was looking at this mural
and just as I was looking
The sun was going down, painting the scene, and
just as I was looking at it
I saw that somebody had put a sticker
right on the railing at the bottom
right in the middle
a big tax wealh not work sticker
and when I see stuff like that it makes me think
that all the hard work is worth it
So that's it, I've got to go
I'll be already in Italy by the time this comes out
we've got a lot going on
some stuff I'm not allowed to speak about yet
cause it's not public
we're trying to do some really exciting stuff
so many offers coming in
we're trying to do some good stuff, tour in Italy
which is happening now. You'd have probably missed it
by the time this comes out
but we'll put the dates out on another short. Australia and
New Zealand tour coming in February
March
I think there's still tickets available
go and check that out
I'm really looking forward to going down under
I'm not quite sure how long we'll be down for
but I think we'll be at least a few months
we'll probably do some specials
in particular around the budget
because the budget's coming out in November
Government's gonna raise taxes
not on the rich
on workers
and people are gonna try to blame me for that
so we'll make some videos to make it very
very very
very clear that we are campaigning to raise taxes
on the very rich, not on working people
we'll probably have to do a special or two around the budget
maybe something end of the year
we'd love to go and meet Gabriel Zukman in France
Jack's been practicing his French especially
we don't know if we’ll manage to figure that out
but I'll be back
and in the meantime, keep watching the videos
keep making stuff, keep creating
keep talking about it
the message is simple
living standards are falling
because of growing wealth inequality
if you don't fix wealth inequality
if you don't fix the tax system
living standards will fall further
tax wealth not work
keep fighting, keep talking about it
I know it's a long fight
and sometimes it can be dispiriting
but I promise you this, we will win in the end
if we didn't win yet
it isn't the end
good luck.