Okay.
So today we're going to do something,
a little bit different.
We're going to be getting involved in the biggest piece
of gossip, slander, some might say libel about me
that took place in the last 6 months while I was away.
We are going to discuss Rory Stewart, his attacks on me,
and we're going to be answering the question:
who is allowed to talk about economics?
Okay, so I'm going to provide just the most basic context
for people who are maybe don't know The Rest is Politics,
don't know Rory Stewart, or are not from this country.
The Rest is Politics
is probably the biggest politics podcast in the UK.
It is hosted by 2 centrist political figures,
a former conservative MP called Rory Stewart,
and a former Labour strategy advisor
under Tony Blair, Alastair Campbell.
And they interviewed Zack Polanski, who is the new sort
of resurgent leader of the Greens, last year in November.
And I became a subject of the conversation and let's...
I'm going to watch, well, I'm going to show you
the... what was said about me back then
so you can see for yourself.
Now tell us which economists you're listening to.
Who are your intellectual influences here?
Brilliant people.
So Grace Blakeley Richard Murphy,
who's been doing a lot of work on this, Gary Stevenson,
who I know you've had on recently, James Medway
or James Meadway.
Lots of different economists, though.
A lot of the time it's just reading the stuff
that they're talking about,
and I think there's a, there is a consensus
that the neoliberal model has broken and does not work.
Consensus where?
From people like Gary Stevenson or where's the consensus?
Where's the academic consensus here?
I think the academic consensus is among economists
who aren't working for the government.
I think they're all looking at government decisions-
And you said Gary Stevenson
as a sort of pseudo-academic economist
or a- I don't think he's pseudo-academic.
I think he's literally an economist.
That's his job.
What about, you mentioned- he-
It's not his job.
He's a city trader.
He studied an undergraduate degree in economics.
Right.
Okay, he's not a professional economist.
But I think if you do a degree
in economics, it's fair to say you're an economist.
Okay, wh-
where are the people with graduate level degrees
in economics that you're focusing on here?
Where are the... where are the professors?
Where are the people who, for whom
this is their academic specialty?
So this underlies-
Okay, so that is Rory Stewart pretty publicly,
denying my credibility as an economist and,
disappearing my postgraduate degree at Oxford.
It's pretty scandalous really.
People who've followed this channel for a long time
will be aware that
it is not uncommon for me to be attacked in the press.
I have been attacked
pretty publicly on YouTube before.
Skinny little dip ****.
And in the newspapers.
And in general, I have, like, a strategy
which is, like, I just don't engage with nonsense
on the internet, nonsense in the newspapers,
and I wasn't going to engage in this one.
But I think something happened
when I was filming the documentary for Channel 4.
So for people who don't know, I was...
I'd been filming a documentary for Channel 4,
which will come out in the next couple of months, and
I was filming that in the last few months of last year,
and this incident was released
while I was filming that documentary.
And I remember I was... I was in a car driving back
from somewhere, doing an interview with probably somebody
horrible, and somebody messaged me on my WhatsApp saying,
"Oh, have you seen this Rory Stewart talking about you
on The Rest is Politics?" And I had a look at it
and I thought, as soon as I saw it, I thought
it was really interesting, and I, I'll tell you why.
So I get attacked a lot in the media.
You know, the Daily Mail ran 4 attack pieces on me
in 4 consecutive days last year.
They knocked on my parents' house.
They went through my mom's Facebook.
The Financial Times wrote a 5,000-word hit piece on me.
And I don't enjoy those kinds of things,
but I've come to expect it.
But what was really interesting
about this attack by Rory Stewart
was most instantly how easily disprovable it was.
So the big attack which sort of my former colleagues
like to come at me with is,
"Gary was not the best trader at Citibank."
It's a very popular attack line from them, and it's smart.
The reason it's smart
is because it's obviously impossible for me
to prove I was the best trader at Citibank.
There's no, like, certificate you can bring out.
And if you're going to attack somebody and say
somebody's a liar, it makes sense to attack them
in a way that they cannot immediately disprove.
But Rory Stewart came out
and implied that I don't have any qualifications
in economics, which is incredibly easily disprovable,
and I, you know, I posted a tweet immediately saying,
"Look, here is my degree." You know,
you get a certificate for it, you can show it.
"Here is my master's degree from Oxford."
And it was, as soon as it came
up, it was in my sort of high school WhatsApp chat.
I said to them, "You know, this--
we will get a public apology from this guy because,
quite simply because otherwise, like, it's a legal risk,
right?" You cannot lie about the qualifications
of probably your biggest commercial rival publicly.
Like, it's, you know, I'm not a lawyer,
but I would imagine you can't get away with that.
So I told them we'd get an apology
and we did get an apology.
And I was going to leave it at that, but then while
I was filming the documentary I started to notice
a sort of a trend happening, which was...
So I've never had any negative interactions
with the public, which is amazing.
I get attacked online all the time.
But I had one negative interaction while I was filming
the documentary, which was I was filming outside
The Treasury, here in the centre of London.
And a guy came out of the Treasury, sort
of a middle-aged guy in his sort of, I guess, late 40s.
And he came up to and he sort of took me by the arm
in quite, like, a tender way, and he came close to me
and he said into my ear, "I just want you to know
you're completely economically illiterate."
And this is a guy who works in the Treasury.
And then over the course of interviewing
some different people, especially people, like, sort of
from this sort of intellectual elite, I started to realise
a kind of narrative, a new narrative was forming
on this global battle against inequality, global battle
for wealth taxes, global battle to improve the economy.
A new sort of very simplistic narrative was forming,
especially from these kind of elites,
which is basically, Gary is an idiot.
Zack Polansky is an idiot.
Don't listen to them
because they're not ******* economists, basically.
And that made me realise that
this sort of new stance represented here by Rory Stewart
and The Rest is Politics, which is just to basically say,
you know, what you would call an ad hominem attack,
which is just to go after the main faces of the movement,
which at the moment in this country
are me and now Zack Polansky, and say, "They're stupid.
Don't listen to them.
They're not got credentials.
They've not got qualifications"
has basically become the core of the movement.
And I think by discussing this incident,
we can learn so much about the state of economics today,
about politics, about the media,
and really where we are at the moment
in the global battle to stop inequality from increasing.
And I think it teaches us
really how we need to act strategically.
So, you know, there's a couple issues to deal with here.
The first one is the basic accusation
of, you know, Gary is not an economist.
Who is an economist?
And the second one is the broader implication
that basically economists do not support wealth taxes.
So let's start with the first one,
and let's answer who is an economist,
who is allowed to talk about economics.
So let's talk a little bit about economics.
Now, economics is one of these specific degrees,
I guess similar to maybe law or computer science or
medicine or dentistry, where there is a broad perception,
or engineering perhaps, there is a broad perception
that these are the degrees that you take
if you want to get a well-paid job.
So economics has this perception
that it is a pathway into well-paid jobs.
And what that means is when you take economics
as an undergrad, a lot of the students there,
from my experience,
I would say the majority of the students are not there
because they are interested in economics.
They are there primarily
because they want to get a good job.
If you go to one of these very elite universities,
and I went to the London School of Economics,
what you will find is the course is generally
incredibly not representative in terms of social class.
So I was at LSE, and really the vast majority
of the people that I studied with, their parents would be
at least millionaires, probably multi, multi-millionaires,
in many cases, very, very wealthy people.
And they are there primarily to get a good job.
So when you're studying economics,
it is an incredibly mathematised discipline.
You spend basically 3 years
in your undergrad mainly really doing a variety
of different kinds of maths, of algebra, of calculus,
all of these different kinds of complicated maths.
And then you basically go and try and get a job.
And because the vast majority of people
who have taken economics are taking it
because they want to get a well-paid job,
the focus for most of these students, rather than
really understanding economics, is getting a good job.
And when I was at university,
and I suspect probably still now,
basically the best paid job you could get
from economics, doing economics, was to work as a trader.
I graduated in 2008.
I was trying to get a job
in sort of 2006, I would say, 2007.
And all the best students in terms of the students
with the best grades wanted to be traders.
I suspect it's probably changed a little bit
over the years.
I guess nowadays you probably do get some economics
students wanting to go into other fields, like maybe AI
or, like, maybe some of these big tech jobs.
But I would guess still
the majority of students want to go into trading.
Really, this question which Rory Stewart
has brought up of, is Gary a real economist, it can
be narrowed down into, like, one incredibly simple concept,
which is there is an academic track
and there is an applied track.
And when you do economics at an elite university,
in my experience, I suspect very much still now,
the vast majority of the students with the best grades
are not trying to go towards the academic track,
for the very simple reason
that the academic track of economics is, on average,
much, much, much less well-paid than the career track,
which is going into finance.
So if you want to become an academic in economics,
you will need to do your 3-year undergrad.
You will need
to do your master's, one or two-year master's.
Then you'll need to do your PhD,
which is probably another 3 years, maybe longer in the US.
Then you need to do postdoc work,
and you need to do more research work,
and you hope to become a professor
maybe in your, into your 30s, by which time
you will be hundreds of thousands of pounds in debt.
And you might start hoping to make money
sometime in your 30s.
Whereas I went into trading in my early 20s, and
I was a millionaire at 25 and a multi-millionaire at 26.
Basically, there is no comparison
between these two tracks in terms of financial outcomes.
So going on the career track,
the applied track, as I've called it here is
the career track, the applied track is just much, much,
much more financially lucrative than the academic track.
So the reality of economics nowadays
is that the vast majority of the students come in
trying to get a well-paid job.
There is enormous competition to get
the best paid jobs, and the vast majority of the students
with the best grades go to work in trading.
You know, this is the truth of the matter.
That's not to say
that some good guys do not stay and go into academia,
but you have to recognise that anyone who has the grades
to go into finance and chooses to stay in academia
is giving up millions of pounds to do that.
And the reality of it is not many people
are going to do that
unless they come from richer backgrounds.
And listen, there are a lot of academic economists
who I have a huge amount of time for
and a huge amount of respect for.
We had the incredibly prestigious
Korean economist Ha-Joon Chang on this channel last year.
There are a couple of French economists that I
really, really like, one of whom at least we're going to try
to get on this year, Gabriel Zucman and Thomas Piketty.
So there are great guys in academia,
but the reality of the situation
is the vast majority of the best students in terms
of the best grades at the most prestigious universities
are not trying to become academics.
They are trying to become, in the large case, traders,
and the best paid 10,000 economists in the world,
in terms of people who are doing economics day to day,
are almost certainly traders.
So I think to sit there and then say "Listen,
I don't want to listen to the opinion of any traders,"
is, like, a little bit absurd.
You know, it's a little bit like saying
you have, like, Cristiano Ronaldo comes on your podcast
and gives his opinions on football, and
you say, "But, you know, have you got a PhD in football?"
And Cristiano Ronaldo says, "No, no, I don't."
It's like, well, where are the people with the PhDs?
You know, because the truth is, in many ways...
I know that sounds like an absurd example,
but economics is, in many ways, similar to football
in the sense of the vast majority of people
who are good at it when they are young
are not trying to become academics.
They are trying to become people
who perform it in the field, you know.
And obviously, it's a little bit of an extreme example,
but this is the case.
You know, there are some disciplines
where the vast majority
students are trying to become professors in that field.
Economics is not one of those disciplines.
The vast majority of people who study economics
are trying to get jobs in finance,
and the most prestigious
and the most well-paid job in finance is as a trader.
But when I heard this news, the first thing
obviously I did is I went on Wikipedia and I looked up
what's Rory Stewart's postgraduate degree,
and he doesn't have one.
And... but the thing is, Rory Stewart
accepted a professorship at Harvard.
So Rory Stewart has been a Harvard professor,
and I think now more recently,
I'm just taking this from his Wikipedia, a Yale professor.
So here you have somebody
with no postgraduate degrees, so he...
And, you know, he worked for government, you know,
so he's obviously has experience in his job.
If you are somebody who has no postgraduate degree and
accepts a professorship at Harvard, so accepts the idea
that you are now an academic expert on your subject
despite never having done a postgraduate degree,
how can you then turn around to somebody who
has a postgraduate degree but also has extreme levels
of success in work and then say your views are invalid?
Like, it's...
Honestly, I just...
You have to say this is tremendously hypocritical.
If you are somebody who believes that people
without postgraduate degrees should not express opinions
on the fields in which they have worked for 20 years,
you cannot accept a professorship at Harvard
based upon the fact that you have experience in work.
You cannot have it both ways.
Either you beli- and I want to make it clear, to be honest,
I don't think postgraduate degrees are that useful, right?
So in economics.
So I have spent 5 years at elite universities.
As much as I have great respect
for some of these economists who I've mentioned
and I think they would probably agree with me,
the experience of studying economics at university,
including at postgraduate level,
is incredibly, incredibly, incredibly depressing.
You know, at Oxford, I was on a course
with 77 people, all of them incredibly smart people,
and they basically locked us in windowless rooms
for 2 years and told us to do simultaneous equations.
And that is basically what happened.
So when I left the London School of Economics
to go to work as a trader,
there's a little story in my book.
Obviously, like most trained university economists,
I thought I could use my, what I learned at university
to sort of help me be a good trader.
And I started as a trader in 2008, and I made it...
You know, there was a big financial crisis.
My first year, I didn't really know what I was doing.
I was just copying people around me.
And I made my first big loss as a trader in 2010,
and I lost $8 million in a week.
And my P&L, my profit and loss, went from
plus 4 million for the year to -4 million for the year.
I was really stressed.
And I instinctively did this thing of I, like, went back
to the books, and I started to bring my economics...
It's funny looking back.
I started to bring my economics textbooks
onto the trading floor.
And when I had a bit of free time, I would, like, sit there
and try and read, try and understand what was happening,
try and understand what I lost money on.
And I was tremendously lucky that
I worked with one of the smartest people I've ever met,
and he must be the best trader I've ever met.
And he in the...
I can't use his real name because he's in the book,
but in the book he's called Billy.
And he was from a working class background,
he didn't go to university, and he worked his way up
over the course of, like, 20, 25 years from being,
like, a cashier at Halifax to being one of Citibank's...
Well, not one of, being Citibank's best trader.
The best trader I've ever met.
Incredibly profitable trader.
And he really looked after me,
and he saw me reading my textbooks on the trading floor,
and he let me do it for a couple of days, and then
I could see he was kind of getting a bit ****** off.
And one day,
he just stood up, he slapped this textbook out of my hand.
It fell into the bin.
The bin fell over, and he just looked at me
and he said, "What the **** are you doing?" Right?
"Like, how old are you?
You know, look around you.
This is...
You're here with the big boys now.
You're betting on what's happening in the real world.
You've lost $8 million,
and the answer is not going to be there in your textbooks.
If you want to know what is happening,
you need to go out there in the real world.
You need to go home
and ask your mom about her financial situation.
You know, you need to look at what's being advertised
on the tube.
You know, walk up and down your local high street.
What shops are opening?
What shops are closing?
Are there more homeless people?
Are there less homeless people?
Talk to your friends and your friends' families
about their financial situation.
If you want to understand what's really happening
in the real world, you need to get out of the books,
and you need to get into the real world." And this guy...
So there's been a lot of controversy,
obviously, about whether I was Citibank's top trader.
I was Citibank's most profitable trader in 2011.
This guy, Billy, was Citibank's most profitable trader
every single other year I was at the bank,
and he never, ever went to university.
And this guy correctly predicted,
before it happened, the 2008 financial crisis.
He correctly predicted the weak recovery
of the 2008 financial crisis.
All of these things
which were none of the rest of us, who were
all sort of elite university educated economists,
none of us predicted it, but he predicted it.
And later on in my career,
I moved from London to Tokyo,
and I was working on the Tokyo trading floor with...
and this guy Billy wasn't there,
and another trader asked me,
"Who do you think is the best economist at Citibank?"
And immediately, without hesitation, I said, "Billy."
Because he obviously was the best economist, right?
Obv-
you know, this guy predicted the 2008 financial crisis.
He predicted the recovery.
You know, he was...
You know, I consider him to be one of the best economists
as well as one of the best traders I've ever met.
And this trader who asked me, he started laughing,
and he replied, "Billy's not an economist."
You know, and his answer was based on the fact
that Billy didn't go to university.
Billy didn't have an economics degree.
But Billy is making bets every single year
based on the, his understanding of the economy,
and he's out-predicting everyone.
But, you know, I think this
really, if I'm totally honest, I think this idea
that Gary is not an economist is exactly the same
as this idea in the book which I encountered as a kid,
which is Billy is not an economist.
I don't think there's really much more behind that
other than really a kind of snobbish elitism, you know?
I think if Rory Stewart thinks I'm not an economist,
he has to give back the money for those professorships,
because how can you
claim to be a Harvard professor level expert
with no postgraduate degrees if you have publicly stated
that nobody without a postgraduate degree
can consider themself an expert in their discipline?
I think it's as...
It's as simple as that.
Like, do you or do you not believe
that somebody can become an expert on a thing
by working in that field?
You know, are the bricklayers ******* expert
in bricklaying because they don't have PhDs?
You know what I mean.
Are the hairdressers experts in hairdressing?
This is a very, very simple idea, Rory Stewart.
It is possible to learn about a thing by doing the thing.
You do not own knowledge in your ivory towers.
It's as...
You know, humans who do not go to university
are still capable of being intelligent.
And let's be quite simple and plain here.
If Rory Stewart says that nobody without a PhD
is an expert in their field,
then he is saying every single one of you
who has done your job for 10, 15, 20 years is an idiot.
It's the truth.
What do you want me to say?
It's the worst kind of elitism.
But listen, I'm getting upset here, but the truth is
that I've had to deal with this my whole ******* life.
My whole ******* life.
I got expelled from school when I was 16,
and I had to go to a new school, and straight away,
"Oh, you didn't really write your essays.
It's plagiarised." My wh- my whole life I've had
to deal with people saying, "Somebody who looks like you,
somebody who sounds like you is not an expert in what
you do, and the things that you produce..." And I knew it.
When I wrote my book, I knew, I knew people would say it,
and I know people still do say it,
"He didn't really write the book." I know it.
I know it.
I know he- I know that's what they're saying.
And I know people constantly say,
"Oh, he wasn't really the best trader." This is...
And I just have to tell myself, "Listen, if you're
so ******* good that people constantly have to say
you didn't really do it, you're not really an expert, then
you're probably ******* good at what you do." All right.
So listen, that's the first thing,
whether you're really an economist.
In my opinion, people who have incredibly
good track records in their field of work are allowed
to be able to claim to be experts in their field of work.
And to be honest, I think Rory Stewart is a politician,
despite not having any postgraduate degrees.
It's as s- in my opinion,
if you have, basically professional experience is valid,
and if you don't believe that, well,
you better get back to a good university
because otherwise you're not allowed to speak.
All right, so we're going to get to the meat
of the argument, which was...
Once we get past the ad hominem personal stuff,
which in my opinion was a little bit stupid,
There is a more substantive economic attack there,
which is elite economists,
like top level economists, do not have a consensus
that we want things like wealth taxes.
So we're going to get to that next.
But I think first we do need, in order for us to be able
to discuss this, to have a little bit of context
on the space in which this attack is happening.
So first thing to say is wealth taxes are relatively new
in terms of how important they are
in the political discourse.
So wealth taxes have been around for a long time.
They've got them even now.
Today they've got them in Switzerland,
they've got them in Norway, they've got them in Spain.
Apparently we're going to have them in Hungary now
because the new government in Hungary
is supportive of a wealth tax.
The ideas have been around for a long time,
but in the last couple of years they have
massively increased in their salience in the discourse.
So salience is this term
which I've been, you know, trying to push on this channel.
Salience is basically how much a thing is spoken about
in the media.
And a big part of the aim of this channel is to increase
the salience of wealth taxes and inequality in terms of
how they affect living standards and the economy.
And I'll be honest, I think we've been incredibly
successful about that, and wealth taxes and inequality
are spoken about much, much, much more in the media.
And that has been happening here in the UK
and across the world
over the last couple of years, not just down to me.
There's been great work by the guys
at Patriotic Millionaires and Tax Justice UK, people
like Bernie Sanders and Elizabeth Warren in the US
have been speaking about it for a long time.
You know, I went and spoke to Chlöe Swarbrick
in New Zealand who's been speaking about it.
But really a big part of it is we have massively, here
on this channel, massively increased
the salience of wealth taxes and inequality in the media.
But for a long time, that was largely all we had achieved.
We had significantly increased the media salience,
but we never won over the Conservative Party
who were in government here for 14 years.
The Labour Party also haven't been won over.
They're not doing it.
So as much as the public wanted it,
and it became an incredibly desirable public policy,
because none of the realistic political parties
in our two-party system
were picking it up, it was basically never going to happen.
Last year that changed,
and that change has to, it has to be credited,
is down almost entirely to the fantastic work
of the new leader of the Greens, Zack Polanski.
So the Greens have had wealth taxes
in their manifesto for a while.
They had wealth taxes
in the manifesto in 2024, the election 2 years ago,
but they didn't really talk about it that much.
And when Zack Polanski
came in, he started to talk much, much more
about inequality, much, much more about wealth taxes.
He did a incredibly energetic social media campaign,
which included making videos and appearing on loads
and loads and loads of different podcasts.
And to be honest, I was incredibly impressed.
I think he... the work he did was fantastic.
The amount of work he did was fantastic,
talking about wealth taxes.
And that led to an enormous increase
in the Greens in the polls.
And the Greens who have always historically been a s- a,
you know, a small/very small British party,
which have never had any significant power or influence
in British politics, suddenly were polling, in many cases
second, or I think there was a poll even last week
where they were polling first.
But, you know, we had polls in which the Greens
were above Labour and above the Conservatives
and that's still happening.
So this is the context of the...
when this interview took place.
The Greens are massively resurgent.
Wealth taxes are massively resurgent.
And as much as we probably won't have an election
in this country for another 3 years,
at the time of the interview 3-and-a-half years,
it was seeming increasingly possible, and it is
increasingly possible that the Greens would or,
could still get into government and that Zack Polanski
would become possibly even prime minister or at
least taking part in some sort of coalition government.
So and you know, we also have the context
of this podcast sort of likes to set itself
as like two opposite sides of the political spectrum
in the two party politics,
which is one guy Labour, one guy Conservative.
But we have this... also this context
of both of these parties collapsing in popularity,
falling down to third and fourth in the polls,
and being basically replaced by 2 new parties.
So it's an incredibly threatening moment for
these two representatives of the political establishment,
but it is also a threatening moment
on basically the elites of the country.
You know, at the moment we have growing and
increasing inequality, and we are also seeing a society
which is becoming increasingly less socially mobile.
If you go to the elite universities,
what you find is a lot of rich, wealthy people.
if you go into elite jobs,
what you find is a lot of rich, wealthy people, people
whose dads were rich, people whose granddads were rich.
And what that means is as we have low social mobility
and we have wealth which is largely inherited
rather than earned, from the perspective
of an ordinary person, what that means is it's hard for
me to make money, it's hard for me to buy a house,
it's hard for me to get a good education,
it's hard for me to get a good job.
But from the perspective of a very elite person,
a very wealthy person, it means the opposite.
It means it's very easy for me to get a good house.
It's very easy for me to get a good job.
It's very easy for me to get a good education.
It's very easy for me to stay at the top.
Low social mobility means poor people stay poor
and rich people stay rich.
So this is like a great setup, basically, for the rich.
So you know, obviously when I saw like Rory Stewart
coming in very aggressively...
So the rest of this interview, which we've not shown,
in my opinion, was a very aggressive attack
by Rory Stewart on Zack Polanski using a method
which I have to be honest, I think is a little bit cheap,
which is he basically sort of pins Zack down and said,
"Can you tell me exactly how large the UK government
debt or deficit, one of these numbers is?" Like, "Tell me
the number, tell me the number." Which is
I've gotta be honest, I think incredibly cheap journalism
to basically say, you know, "Have
you memorised this number before you came on this show?"
Listen, we can all look that number up.
We can all Google that number.
Zack Polanski is not an economist, you know.
if you want to do that, you sh-
you should have done it to me when I went on the show.
I was on the show a couple of months earlier.
But what I saw when I watched
that was, I think, an incredibly aggressive attack.
So obviously, the first thing I wanted to do was I want
to understand, is this guy part of a very wealthy family?
I don't know Rory Stewart's family background,
but I just did the most basic research.
I went on his Wikipedia, and I...
The first thing I wanted to see
was, is your dad's name blue and underlined?
I've gotta be honest, like, that-
that's the first thing I want to see nowadays, right?
And then I...
And it was, and I've gotta be honest,
that was a long ******* article.
It's got about 10 sections there,
and, apparently, he was educated in a castle
and was, according to Wikipedia, one of the
most powerful men in the secret services of the country.
Once we recognise this as an attack for what it is,
that doesn't mean in and of itself the attack is bad.
And I think when we view, the meat of the attack
is that, listen, economists in general,
academic economists in general,
do not agree with this idea
that wealth taxes are good, that wealth taxes are needed.
There is no consensus for this.
And that attack in itself is partially true,
and I want to be clear.
I've been very, very clear
about that from the beginning of this channel, right?
If it was true that there was a consensus
among academic economists that we needed
to reduce inequality, and we needed to do wealth taxes,
then there would be no need for me to do this channel.
There would have been no need for me
to have left trading, and quite frankly, like,
I wouldn't be a multimillionaire, right?
The reason that I was attracted to this idea
about wealth taxes, about inequality
was specifically for the reason that
I recognised this important fact was missing
from the broad academic economic consensus.
You know, if you want to know sort of the history,
we've done some videos about it,
or you can read it
in my book, The Trading Game, available in all good stores.
I developed these ideas
in the context of being a graduate of, in economics,
a graduate of the London School of Economics,
and then working on the trading floor
and witnessing a series, a consistent series
of really strong failures to predict the broad economy.
So I studied my undergrad 2005 to 2008, and then
I start working as a trader in the middle of 2008.
There's a massive financial crisis
which nobody predicted.
But then
what was more interesting to me was the aftermath
of the crisis was also incredibly badly predicted.
And in 2008,
an aggressive recovery was predicted for 2009.
In 2009, an aggressive recovery was predicted for 2010.
In 2010, an aggressive recovery was predicted in 2011,
and the beginning of 2011, we were still seeing,
massive aggressive recoveries predicted.
And I was working full time
all that time in the field of predicting interest rates.
And, you know, interest rates are broadly linked
to the strength of the economy,
so everybody thought interest rates would come back up,
and they never did.
And I was sitting there 2008, 2009, 2010,
the beginning of 2011 realising, like, ***** like,
we are really consistently wrong on, like, this
really, really big issue,
which is basically like, is the economy going to get better?
Is your life going to get better?
Like, year after year after year after year.
And it was in that...
I would like to add, you know, that didn't...
That wasn't just '08 to '11.
You know, this constant prediction that
things will get better next year lasted all the way to
2020, and if you look at the prediction of interest rates,
which is broadly connected to the prediction
of the strength of the economy, they predicted
things would get better every single year for 13 years.
And it was only in 2020, in the middle of COVID,
when economists suddenly started saying,
"Oh, no, actually, interest rates will stay 0 forever."
And that's immediately before interest rates went to 6%.
So, you know, when I was there for 3 years, what
I saw was this phenomenal bad track record of predicting,
and that phenomenal bad track record of predicting
has continued to this day.
And what you see is continual, in basically every field,
continual over-optimistic prediction of the economy.
For me, as somebody
who has been at the elite universities
and then watched the predictions,
what I see is, like, this phenomenal track record
of making bad predictions again and again and again.
And I think, the scientific thing to do
when you see
that your predictions are incredibly, consistently wrong,
incredibly, consistently bad, is to look at your beliefs
and look at your model for understanding the world
and try to understand what is missing in the model.
And I think that this is the logical thing to do here,
and that's what I did back in 2011.
I came to the conclusion that I still believe, that
what is missing is the significance of the importance
of the wealth distribution and increasing inequality
on living standards, on the macroeconomy.
And betting on this has made me millions and millions
of pounds back in 2011 and 2012 but also since COVID.
Incredibly good track record of prediction.
I think it works incredibly well.
But I think there is a strong case to be made that
in an economy where living standards are continually
worsening and expert academic predictions
are continually wrong, I think there should be space to
have a debate that says maybe there is something
wrong with the broad economic consensus.
But Rory Stewart's philosophical position
seems to be anyone who says anything
that goes against the broad economic consensus
should not be listened to.
This to me is incredibly worrying.
I, you know,
I think if you are in a situation where,
you know, if this is like every single time
a patient goes to a doctor they're dying, right?
Every single... anyone goes to a doctor, they die,
and then somebody says, "Hey, like, maybe
we should have a look at what the ******* guys,
doctors are doing in the hospital.
Maybe they're doing something wrong."
And Rory Stewart turns around
says, "Hey, are you a doctor?" You know, this is,
this is incredible amount of, to be honest,
like... it's incredibly hubristic intellectual gatekeeping,
this idea that me and my people, I know we've been wrong
for 20 years, and I know you've been right for 15 years,
but do you have the certificate?
You know, if you don't, **** off.
But the thing is I actually did
what surely Rory Stewart would have recommended
that I do, which is I quit my job,
and I was making millions of pounds a year,
and I went back into academia, right?
So I went back into academia,
and I did a 2-year master's, which is like a kind of...
It's called a MPhil at Oxford.
It's like a special, like big master's,
so it's not a PhD, but it's bigger than a master's.
I started that in 2017, and you know,
obviously I was particularly interested in this one idea
that I had, which is inequality is not being talked
about enough, and that's making our predictions wrong, and
it's making living standards fall.
And in particular, I was interested in its effect
on interest rates because that was what I traded
and that was what I consider myself
to be a legitimate expert in.
And interest rates are something
which is discussed extensively in academia,
and they were brought up
in one of our first lectures in my Master's at Oxford.
And I waited behind after that lecture, and
I spoke to the professor, and I said to him, "Hey, like, can
we talk about why our predictions, like broad economists,
our predictions for interest rates have been so bad
for so long?" And he wasn't aware of
the bad track record of prediction of interest rates.
He was like, "Oh, what are talking about?" I was like,
"Well, you know, we always said
that rates were going to come back up very quickly,"
but by this time, 2017, rates had stayed at 0 for 9 years.
And he turned around to me, and he said,
"Oh, like, no, we always knew rates were going to stay 0,"
which is like incredibly, categorically provably wrong.
And I was quite like surprised that here is this Oxford
professor teaching interest rates at Oxford University
who is unaware
that interest rates have been mispredicted for 9 years.
I've got to be honest, like I was quite shocked.
And I said, "Okay, I'm going to go, I'm going to go home,
and I'm going to send you the data, and you're going to see
that your predictions have been wrong
for 9 years." And I went, and I sent him the data,
and he was, "Oh, you're right, yeah.
Our predictions have been wrong for 9 years."
And that was it.
He didn't want to talk any more about it.
He wasn't...
And this was like, it's mind-blowing to me, you know.
It's, th- this is...
And, I just want to be clear.
You can go and watch the article of Rest Is Politics.
I told Rory Stewart
this story on the Rest Is Politics, right?
So, you know, I am somebody who was in academia, left
academia, went and had an enormous amount of success.
I was one of the top students there.
I got my first in 2 years, right?
I spent the third year just getting drunk
because my grades were so good, basically.
Left academia, went into the city, had an enormous amount
of success, came back into academia,
and I've gotta be honest, what I saw in academia,
I cannot describe to you how dreadfully bad
it was, how dreadfully, dreadfully, dreadfully bad it was.
All right.
But let's push back even further because I think
it's actually giving too much credit to this argument
to say that there is not a consensus because whilst
it is true that there is not a broad economic consensus
on inequality and wealth taxes, there are some excellent...
some of the most prestigious economists in the world
that are incredibly passionate about this issue, right?
The most obvious of which is Thomas Piketty.
Thomas Piketty's book I've got.
It's wrapped in this lovely way
because I bought it in Japan just after it came out.
Thomas Piketty.
So this guy, Thomas Piketty,
he won the French Economics Association's award
for the best thesis of the year in 1993.
He was the 2002 best young economist in France,
one of the most prestigious economists in the world.
And what does he work on all the time?
What does he talk about all the time?
Inequality.
Gabriel Zucman,
who won the French Economic Association's award
for the best dissertation in
2014, what does he work on?
What is he passionate about?
Inequality.
So I just think this idea
that no economists support it is just wrong.
It's as simple as that, right?
So I mean, I don't know what...
Really when you dig behind the substance
here, what you have is an incredibly elitist stance,
that is also, like, quite simply wrong.
Like, lots of elite economists
are incredibly passionate about this, even ones
who haven't done such grubby, mucky work
as trying to make actual money as a professional trader.
And what I see here when I see people push back
on this really is you have, in my opinion,
unfortunately, a tremendously out of touch elite class
that is incredibly unwilling to accept the, I would say,
like increasingly obvious truth that living
standards are falling, and things have to change.
So I spoke in last week's video about the absolute collapse
of the political centre, and the mainstream
political parties who have dominated politics in Europe
for the last, you know, 100, 200 years.
Basically all of them are collapsing.
And this is very relevant
in the context of the Rest is Politics podcast,
because the whole idea of the Rest is Politics podcast
is it is based on the idea of 2-party politics,
which is we have the Labour Party,
the traditional centre-left party,
and the Conservative Party,
the traditional centre-right party.
These guys are on opposite sides of the coin,
and, you know, if we have these two guys,
then we can see things from 2 different angles.
But the fact is both of these political parties
are absolutely collapsing in power and popularity,
and that is happening not just here in the UK,
but it is happening across the entire world.
And I think people like Rory Stewart
and people like Alastair Campbell, if
they had their eyes open, they would be looking at that.
They should be saying,
"Why are not just our political parties,
UK Labour and UK Conservatives, collapsing in popularity,
but why are all global centrist parties
collapsing in popularity?" I think it's...
You don't have to take much distance
to look at the world and say, "Something is wrong."
And I think this response of Rory Stewart
to say, "You, Zack Polanski,"
you know, and also me, I went on the podcast
and I was mentioned, "Gary Stevenson, you want change,
but is there a consensus from academics like me
that things should change?"
If... You can't help but be reminded
of this famous Marie Antoinette quote, "Let
them eat cake." You know, it's incredibly obvious,
to anyone who's watching, that way of
seeing politics and that way of doing economics is dying.
And yet when somebody new comes in
and says, "Let's do things different," you turn around
and say, "Oh, but where's the academic consensus?"
Well, the setup of economics is it is very unlikely
that anybody who is very good at economics
from a poor background is going to stay.
There's very strong mechanisms.
Take somebody like me, you know, top of my class
at LSE, but from a poor background.
I can't realistically afford to become an academic when
houses in London, a flat in London costs £500,000, £600,000.
You know, if it...
I'm choosing a life of poverty.
And then the end result is the vast majority of people
in academic economics are people like Rory Stewart,
whose dads have got blue underlined names
on Wikipedia, right?
Because they are the guys who could afford to do it.
So basically you're turning around
and saying, "Listen, we are only...
I am only going to even countenance change
if it is accepted by the elite class."
But when you have an economic crisis of inequality,
that actively enriches the elite class.
So you have this situation,
you know, crises of inequality, it...
We are not all getting poorer here.
The last 20 years have not been bad for the top 1%.
They've been fantastically good
for the top 0.1%, and they've been okay for the top 5%.
How many people are there with those PhDs in economics
in the top universities who are not from the top 5%?
What you are saying is, "We will not accept any change
on growing inequality unless
it is mandated by the group of people who are benefiting
from the increase in inequality." I think what
we are seeing here is actually so, so interesting,
and I don't think it's overplaying
it to say that this is, what we are witnessing, the death,
really, of a form of intellectualism.
So I think for me, for something to be a science
or close to a science or a good field of study,
it is incredibly important that ideas are open
to challenge, and it is incredibly important
that culturally powerful figures
who are powerful in a discipline but are wrong
are able to be challenged by people who are less
well-known and less powerful but are correct.
If you do not have that in your science,
then what you have is not a science anymore.
It becomes essentially a dogma.
You know, there's this story about calligraphy
in medieval China.
So calligraphy, obviously, China has this, like Japan,
this system of writing characters.
You need to learn thousands of characters.
And apparently in medieval China, if you wanted to get
an important job, you needed to memorise the perfect way
to paint with a brush, like 10,000 Chinese characters.
And what this meant was basically
because it was incredibly expensive
to educate somebody to learn over many, many years
how to paint these 10,000 characters
perfectly, nobody could enter the intelligentsia
who was not from a rich family,
because nobody could afford the education
that was essential to be in that world.
And what you are seeing here
with this Rory Stewart gatekeeping of the word economist
is basically that exact thing, which is you are not
allowed to question the knowledge of my people
unless you are one of my people.
And this is incredibly frustrating because
economics in particular is not a physical science.
It does not have experiments.
So obviously I have a thesis here, which is
that living standards are falling because of inequality.
And I wrote my first video in June 2020
saying living standards will fall, inflation
will rise, house prices will rise, stock prices
will rise, the gold price will rise.
You'll get government austerity,
you'll get an inflation crisis
on the back of this thesis.
And a lot of people, you know, that looks in hindsight
like it was good, but you will have some economists
that will say, "No, you know, you're wrong.
It wasn't to do with the increase of inequality,
it was, you know, because of different things.
It was because of maybe the Ukraine war." I'm
sure people will say now it was because of the Iran war.
There's no way for us to run the clock backwards
and do an experiment
where we say, "Imagine we had COVID again, but
we didn't significantly increase the government deficit,
we didn't significantly increase inequality,
we funded things like lockdown by taxing rich people,
would you still see the same level of inflation?"
There's no way for us to run that experiment,
so there's no way for us
to say categorically Gary was right, and there's no way
for them to say categorically Gary was wrong,
because we can't do a physical experiment on it.
Obviously, you can look at some cases like Switzerland.
They didn't run the massive government deficit.
They didn't get the inflation.
But the fact is, we can't run an experiment.
And this is why, for me, prediction
of the future is so important, specifically in economics.
Because if we have a situation where
we cannot run experiments to see whose ideas are right
and whose ideas are wrong, we need a way
to get a sense of who has a correct understanding
of what is happening in our economy.
Otherwise, when we end up in situations
like we are in now, when living standards fall
for a long period of time, for 20 years, in what seems
to be an accelerating way, and living standards
will probably continue to fall, we will be unable
to recognise who are the economists we should listen to
when we are considering how to fix it.
The private sector, trading, has this very aggressive way
of deciding who to listen to, which is you
simply look for people who have consistent track records
of correctly predicting things
that nobody else predicted at the time.
So this is why when I wrote my first articles
and when I wrote my first videos,
and even now today, I consistently, as often
as I can, try to make clear predictions about the future
and try to make it clear
that these predictions are not consensus at the time.
And it's also
why I try to make a number of different predictions.
You know, when I came out at the beginning of COVID,
I didn't just say,
"There's going to be a cost of living crisis,"
I said, "It will be paired with increasing house prices
and increasing stock prices
and increasing gold prices." You know, this is...
And, increasing inflation.
This is a unexpected combination of things to happen.
None of those things were consensus predictions
at the time.
I think when you come out and you correctly predict
a lot of things at once that nobody's predicting
at the time, you know, after doing the same thing
in the aftermath of 2008, that gives you a right
to challenge an elite establishment that is consistently
predicting things wrong.
But what Rory Stewart is saying here is, in my opinion,
like really fundamentally anti-scientific.
Which is to say we should not listen to people
who have a long-term track record of being right
when they are competing against people
who have a long-term track record of being wrong
if they are in the field of work
rather than in the field of academia.
And it's incredibly frustrating for me.
You know, this...
When I was at school, I was... I was very good at English
as well as maths.
And when I was young, I was sort of choosing,
am I going to do, like, English and law, or am
I going to do, like, maths, and then try to get into finance?
And at the end of the day, the reason I chose maths
is because I got a D in my one exam,
my William Blake exam, A-level English Literature.
And it made me realise, like, I'm never putting my future
in the hands of, like, the subjective analysis
of some posh person again, basically.
And in maths, I'm really confident.
You give me the question, I'll put you the right answer.
And in trading it's the same.
I'm really confident
my predictions will be correct.
And that is why I've chosen these fields where
the judgment is largely objective rather than subjective.
Was the prediction right?
Is the answer right?
But it's incredibly frustrating
to continually generate these predictions
which can be seen afterwards to be correct, can
be seen afterwards to be much better than the mainstream,
and can be seen afterwards to be predicting
that living standards will get worse for the masses
and better for the elites,
and then to be told by incredibly rich people, "We are
not going to listen to you because the elites don't agree."
Yeah, it's incredibly frustrating.
And I think this is really the heart
of where the wealth tax argument is at the moment.
And when establishment
figures from established political parties like Labour,
like Rory Stewart, turn around to new figures
who are saying, "We're going to do something to change,"
like Zack Polanski, and say, "You are an idiot,"
the public are going to rightly be ****** off
because the public are going to say,
"Well, what is your plan for change?" I think until and
unless the political centre, be that centre right or
centre left, Conservatives, Labour, Democrats, Republicans,
whoever it is in your country,
until these central political parties
have some sort of realistic, meaningful plan for how
they are going to change the management of the economy
so it stops delivering
consistently falling living standards, every time
they turn around to somebody like Zack Polanski
or somebody like me and says, "We're not listening to you,
you know, because you're an idiot,"
the public are going to see that and say, "Well, what
the **** is your plan then?" And I think this is going to...
I think it's only going to make Zack Polanski
more popular.
And I think Zack Polanski's
done this incredibly intelligent thing
of he continually repost all the attacks on him.
And what he's saying
is, "Listen, these guys are driving you off the cliff, and
all they're doing is calling me an idiot." You know, who...
Whether you like Zack Polanski or not, Rory Stewart
or anyone else in Labour or the Conservatives,
you need to have a credible plan for change.
All right, so that is the last thing.
Now we move on to our final point,
which is what do we do about this?
Because the first thing to recognise
is they're only attacking people like Zack Polanski
and people like me because
we are in an incredibly, incredibly strong position.
The centre is collapsing.
The far right is quite weak at the moment.
At the moment, I don't really see any other group
or any other idea which is, like, gaining momentum
at the speed with which we are gaining momentum.
I think you should support people like Zack,
and anyone in your country
who is pushing for wealth taxes.
You know, in Australia and New Zealand, that's the Greens.
But it's different people in different countries.
You know, whatever, a Bernie Sanders
or Elizabeth Warren in the US.
Support the people who are doing the work.
I think when I look at Zack Polanski,
I'm someone who's done media campaigns
and has gotten attacked in the press, and I just
want to say, like, it's ******* hard and it's annoying,
and it's having people just, like, attacking you
and calling you a *********
then, you know, people come at Zack at the way he looks
and you know, it's just stupid, nonsense stuff.
And I just want to say, like, well done to that guy
for keeping on going.
And,
you know, whatever you think about his other policies,
in my opinion, if what you care about is the economy,
in our current situation, while there is
only one political party that's supporting wealth taxes,
you do need to support this guy who's going out there
and getting **** thrown at him every day.
But we also need to build that academic credibility
because I think at the moment,
the reason that the Rest Is Politics
and Rory Stewart have been able to, in my opinion,
kind of slander the wealth tax with this idea
that the main two proponents of the wealth tax
in this country, me and Zack Polanski, are idiots,
are not serious.
That is only possible, in my opinion, because of classism.
I don't think there is any reading of my professional
and academic history that says anything
other than this guy is a serious expert on inequality.
But he's able to do that
because, you know, he looks and sounds like what
smart people are supposed to look and sound like
in this country, and I look and sound like this.
So we do need, especially in a country like the UK,
which has a long history of classism,
we need academics.
So I have reached out to, in my opinion,
the best guy in the world,
in terms of academics, who is doing this,
which is a guy called Gabriel Zucman,
who is an incredibly prestigious French economist
who has been doing work on inequality for a long time.
He has been really pushing wealth taxes in France.
He's been doing fantastic work.
I've been in touch with Gabriel Zucman
since I think 2014 was the first time I spoke to him.
These guys, Piketty and Zucman
and Saez, they are the world leaders in inequality,
and I think what we really need, and
I'm going to hope that they support us on this, is we need...
Where there are academics who look
and sound like academics, we need them
to help people like me and Zack, who are much stronger
on social media but don't look and sound like academics.
We need them to come and just make
it, like, painfully obvious what is true, which is that
a lot of serious academic economists support this idea.
So we've reached out to him.
He's accepted an interview.
We're going to have him on in May.
I think I will reach out to Thomas Piketty as well,
and we're just going to show the British public,
and the global public
that this is... that academics believe this.
We can't allow this basically libellous slander
that academics don't believe this
because academics do believe this.
We're going to get them on the channel.
But I think it's also important that we do not allow
ourself to be, like, battered into this lane
that unless the academics say it's correct,
then it's not, it's not going to be correct.
So, you know, I've done loads of videos
on the problems with academic economics.
We'll flash them up now.
There's one called The World of Economics.
The best one is probably Why Economists Are Always Wrong.
I think there's one called Why Your Economists Suck.
I've done it loads.
This one, Why Your Economists Are Always Wrong,
is me walking around Oxford,
so if you want a bit of ASMR in the background for you.
Academic economics is in a position
where it basically doesn't look at inequality,
which means that the vast majority of professors
who have been doing macroeconomics for 20 years
have no knowledge on inequality,
have no serious knowledge of inequality, which means that
they have a very strong vested interest in believing and
putting out the idea that the problem is not inequality
because if the problem is inequality,
then they have nothing really to say about the problem.
So the truth is, you know,
we are going to keep getting pushback from economists,
and the economists are by and large wrong.
So I don't think we can accept this idea
that until there is a broad economic consensus,
something... you know, nothing should be done.
We do need to also keep building
up this other channel, which I think we are building.
So I think at the moment, like, there's kind of, I think,
a few different angles of attack we can use, right?
One of them is political parties,
and I said last week, join a political party,
whether it's Greens, whether it's Labour.
You know, I said, last week,
and I still stand by it.
Even if it's Reform, I don't care.
Join your political parties
and get them to do something about wealth taxes.
If nobody's doing something about wealth taxes,
support the political party that is doing it,
which is Zack Polanski and the Greens.
Sign up to vote.
We did the big sign up to vote last week.
We'll flash it up again.
This is where you sign up to vote.
We'll put it in the description.
Sign up to vote because we need to pressure them.
We need more academics,
but also, I think the real good angle of attack,
and I think where we have made so much progress...
Obviously, I would say this, but I do think it is true.
The real big angle of attack here is social media.
I think the reason that this has become such a big issue
is largely because of the enormous success
we have had here in bringing this issue
to the public, and I want to talk a little bit, just briefly,
about the importance of social media.
So there, there's this idea
that I've been putting around recently.
You guys don't see this work.
In the background, I'm doing a lot of ******* lobbying
of people to try to get them to be more serious
about social media because in my opinion,
it is really obvious that political power is moving,
has been moving, will continue to move away
from traditional media like newspapers and TV and radio
and towards social media.
And that means that whichever sort of political ideas
are big on social media will have a really good chance
of getting enacted.
We're changing policy here.
We haven't done it in the UK yet,
but we are changing it across the world, right?
Because of this enormous pressure
that we're pushing on social media.
So I think the optimal model for politics
in social media is what I've been calling the WWF model.
WWF, which is now called WWE, is American wrestling, and
you go onto American wrestling and there's like, you know,
when I was a kid sort of 10, 15, 20,
now it's probably 30, 40, 50, like faces.
Like all these different characters,
like, you know, big characters.
And, you know, these guys are a little group, and
these guys hate these guys, and these guys are together,
and those guys don't like these guys.
And I think that is a really, really powerful model
for politics and social media,
which is basically you have all these different people
doing all these different things,
and then when people come in and look at social media,
they think, "Oh, wow, what an exciting space
with all these different people in it."
And I think the only real group of people
who have succeeded in creating that kind
of like social media product, which is full of all
these different characters, is the US alt-right, far-right,
or whatever you want to call them.
And I think that is a big part of the reason
for the growth of the alt-right and the far-right
across the world, especially amongst young men.
Because basically they've created this
like social and exciting social media product.
And I think, to be honest,
if you want to be serious about like stopping the,
the global growth of the far right, we do need to create
a social media product which is focused on wealth taxes
and inequality, which is similar in this same way.
So really I think here on this channel,
I think what we need to do is we...
To be honest, there's lots we need to do.
We need to build out.
We need to be better connected.
We need to be able
to support new, like influencers who are coming up
so that we can build new faces and names.
And that's why I've been like so keen on trying to like
support and keep mentioning people like Louisa Munch,
and Barry's Economics, and Anna Bocca, and Jimmy the Giant.
Like, I really want to support these names because I think
in the absence of like a powerful political force,
and, you know, giving all the credit
that is due to the work that Zack Polansky has done
in the massive growth of the Greens.
If Labour don't move, which it seems
like they're not going to move, we need to create a space
which is so big that basically when the new Labour
leader comes in, they've got no choice to move.
But we also need to be better linked up, better connected.
We need better connections to politicians.
One of the reasons why I've been traveling the world
is to try to like find good people in
different countries who are also pushing this,
I've been really happy to meet Chlöe Swarbrick
in New Zealand, who's doing great work.
But basically we need to build this.
We need to be better connected.
We need to be better connected to politicians.
We need to be better lobbyists.
And if I'm going to be totally honest,
we need on this channel to be better funded.
It is largely me and my mate Oscar trying
to run around, do everything on this YouTube channel.
Yeah, I think we...
If we want this to be bigger, we need staff.
We need staff.
Which is why we're going to move on.
We are going to move on to a pitch to the Patreon I think.
I think if you want to be serious...
You know, you don't have to give money to the channel.
There's loads of things you can do.
You can create your own stuff.
You can support the videos.
You can push it.
But I think if we want to make this a movement,
we do need...
Really what we need is a lobbyist, to be honest.
Because we're sitting here, we're going to grow the channel
as much as we can, but where we have really failed
is in linking ourselves up to like other groups
internationally, other groups in this country,
and in building good connections
with the political parties.
Hopefully, we'll get some growth off of the
the documentary, which will come out later this year.
But I think that's what we need to do.
We need to lobby better.
We need to be better connected.
We need to grow this channel,
and we need to grow other channels.
But it is getting to the point
really where I can't do that, and we do need staff.
So we're going to put the Patreon up.
The Patreon is set up as a not-for-profit company,
so none of the money goes to me.
None of the money can possibly go to me.
It all goes towards hiring staff.
And it would be nice to build something
a little bit more serious here so that we can,
so that we can win this I think.
Yeah, centre's dying.
the far right is weak.
The future's there to be won.
So that's the end of the Patreon pitch.
I'll have to do that at least once a season
because otherwise we can't afford
to make these videos anymore.
But that's it basically.
Look, the last thing I want to say
is honestly, this is not a joke.
This is deadly serious.
I have got a lot of respect for Rory Stewart, honestly.
I loved his book.
I thought it was...
the only reason I don't have his book
to show you is because I lent it to my mate
because I thought it was so good, Politics on the Edge.
It's hilarious really, to be honest.
And he really supported my book.
You know, I think...
This is not me advertising it.
I don't know if you see this.
On the quote on the front of my book is...
Can you get that?
It's Rory Stewart because he gave a great quote.
And look, I don't think he's a bad guy.
I just think he's...
I actually think he's super interesting.
I think he's a great writer.
I think it's so interesting that
he like somehow like forgot that I had a postgraduate
degree, and I think it really tells you so much about how
he needs to create a narrative that him and his guys
are not the bad guys and the status quo is not bad.
And, you know, that's normal.
You know, it's normal for people to be scared,
and it's normal for him to be scared,
and it's normal for him to be challenged.
And, Rory Stewart, you are...
You know, I loved your book.
You know, I enjoyed coming on your channel.
You're more than welcome if you want to come here
and discuss anything we've said today.
Yeah, I can have you on anytime.
I think you're a really interesting guy.
But look, what you are seeing here is more and more
every day it's a political vacuum, right?
The centre is crumbling.
The world is there to be won.
I think there's so much, so much, so much opportunity,
and I'm going to...
What I'm going to really try to do this season
as much as I can, as much as my sort of energy
and mental health allow, try to help build up these other...
these other influencers, try to be better connected.
But yeah, look, support us.
Register to vote.
Be ready to push.
And just stay cool.
Don't stress out because which is something
that I've probably failed to do in this video.
Yeah, we're going to be here.
Sorry for doing so many long videos recently,
but there was just so many, so much crazy stuff
to catch up on.
Hopefully next week will be shorter.
But yeah, thank you very much for your time.
Tax wealth, not work.
And sign up to vote.