Okay. Well, back to Gary's economics.
Today we are doing the video that
I was strongly advised not to make.
And we are going to tell you
who you need to vote for
in this week's local elections.
If you want to stop the collapse
in living standards.
All right.
So the basic context
for our foreign friends or British
people
who are not particularly interested
in local elections,
which is quite a lot
because local elections
tend to get ignored.
We have local elections coming up
this week, coming on the seventh,
which is the Thursday
this coming week.
And you need to vote
in these elections
because they are particularly
big ones.
They're really important.
Really, this is the closest
you are going to get to a vote for
who is going to be your next prime
minister if you're here in the UK.
So local elections
do tend to get ignored.
They don't change the Prime Minister,
although this one quite
possibly might.
But this one is really,
really important.
First of all, we've
got a few big elections going up.
It's going to decide the new
government in Scotland and in Wales.
The second big reason
why this is important
is because if you watched my video
a few weeks ago,
I spoke about how the established
political parties in the UK,
like in the rest of the Western world,
are basically collapsing.
And we have a situation now where
historically, for hundreds of years
the UK has been a two party
political system,
and in the next election
we will have genuinely six
or maybe even seven parties
that have a big say on
who will be the next prime minister.
And these local elections are going
to be basically a big battling ground
to decide which political parties
are considered to be
like the serious contenders
for the next election.
It's particularly important,
obviously, for Labour,
who are incredibly unpopular,
and everybody will be looking
to see how badly they do.
It's going to be really important
for the Greens, who are...
There's a kind of battle
going on at the moment
in the UK to determine basically
who is the legitimate person or party
to vote for if you want to prevent
a Reform government
in the next German election.
That was a big story in the recent
by elections in Manchester.
And I think there's going to be
a big thing here
about whether the Greens
are the more legitimate anti
Reform party in this country,
In contrast to Labour.
It will be important also for Reform
who are well ahead in the polls
but are seeming to
lose a bit of popularity
because of Donald Trump doing things
which are hurting living standards
and quite internationally unpopular.
So it's going to be massive
in deciding
like who are the runners and riders
for the next election?
Basically, like will
the established political parties,
Labour and Conservatives disappear
or will they not?
And the third main reason
why this is super important is because
there is a realistic possibility
that Keir Starmer will resign
after the local elections.
So the context on that is that Keir
Starmer is polling incredibly badly.
He is incredibly unpopular.
He's apparently the least
popular British prime minister
in the history of polling.
There's a lot of controversy right now
about Peter Mandelson
and Jeffrey Epstein
and all this stuff going on,
but it is very possible
that if Labour do
incredibly badly in this election,
he will be forced out.
As a betting man,
I should probably talk a little bit
about how likely that is.
The market
thinks there's about a 50% chance
that Starmer goes before September.
and about a 66% chance
he goes this year.
I actually think
that is quite possible
they'll keep him on a bit longer,
but really, we don't know.
But it is very possible.
We can't say with certainty,
but if it's not immediately or in the
in the immediate period
after these, these local elections
that Starmer will go, I think it's
very, very likely that he will go.
He will be forced to resign either
this year or next year,
which means that we will get here
in the UK, a new Prime Minister,
and these local elections
are going to have a big influence
on who
the next Prime Minister will be.
So if and when Keir Starmer resigns,
the new prime minister will be decided
within the Labour Party,
between the MPs and the members.
And you,
as an ordinary British person,
if you're watching from the UK,
will not be able to vote in that.
So the closest
you will have to a vote on deciding
who will be the new Prime Minister,
what would be the new direction
for this country will probably be
in these elections this week.
And the final reason
why these local elections
are important,
and that you definitely need to vote
in these local elections, is because
we did a massive call out about it.
I think it was three weeks ago.
We did a video.
We posted the link
on how to register to vote.
If you haven't registered yet,
it's too late,
so make sure you register
for the next one.
But we have decided to sort of step
in a little bit on this and try to be
a little bit more assertive
and a little bit more aggressive
in getting our viewership to vote
and to participate.
And the reason that we've done
this is because really,
we want to build a bit of ability
to influence the Labour Party.
So if you've been watching
this channel
for a long time,
you will know that we've grown
very quickly
in the last couple of years.
And we have a very clear mission
on this channel,
which is we want to stop the growth
in wealth inequality.
We want to stop the growth
in economic inequality.
We want to improve living standards,
and we want to do that
by pressuring governments
here in the UK and across the world,
wherever you are, to build a fairer
tax system which taxes wealth,
very wealthy people more and taxes
work, taxes working people less.
That's why we call it
tax wealth, not work.
And we've been quite frustrated.
I've been quite frustrated,
especially in the last
couple of years,
because we have done a great job
of making
wealth taxes and fairer tax system
incredibly popular with the public.
But center left political parties
such as Labour
or the Democrats
or the center left party,
wherever you are, have generally been
incredibly resistant
to these cause on wealth taxes,
and in the UK in particular,
Labour have been pretty reluctant
to even speak to me about policy.
I did a documentary recently
for Channel Four and they didn't.
They refused to let me speak to
anybody from the Treasury.
And it's been quite frustrating
because I think we've created
a situation where if Labour
want to save the economy,
if they want to stop living standards,
or even if Labour just want
to, like, not,
you know,
keep losing elections really badly.
I think that
they should be speaking to me.
And I've been trying my best
to let them know
if anyone out
there is watching from Labour.
We'd love to speak to you
and email us on this email address.
But we've been really pushing
to build a relationship
where we advise Labour
to some degree on on policy.
And they've been really,
really reluctant.
And while Labour has been ignoring us,
we've had this emergence of
a new leadership of the Green Party,
which has really enthusiastically
adopted our ideas on inequality
and on wealth taxes.
And has rapidly increased
its popularity and has rapidly
increased its vote share. And
we, I
always hoped that if Labour didn't
listen,
to be honest, I always anticipated
something like this would happen.
My theory was always that if you make
if you create a public
which is enthusiastically supportive
of wealth taxes, either
Labour will have to talk to you or
somebody else will pick up the idea.
They will start to steal Labour's
vote share
and then Labour
will have to talk to you.
But unfortunately,
we've now reached the situation
where that has started to happen.
Labour are now
sort of being destroyed in the polls,
both on their right by Reform
and now on the left by the Greens
and Labour are still
incredibly reluctant to talk to us.
So we're trying to take a little bit
more of an assertive,
aggressive strategy
where we say to Labour, listen, either
you talk to us
or we will start telling our vote
to vote against you, start telling
our viewership to vote against you.
So if you want wealth taxes,
and you're supporting the message
of this channel, it's very important
that you vote in these elections
because we are trying
to use these elections
to try and persuade Labour
to give us something on wealth taxes
Okay, so we did our big call out
three weeks ago.
We really requested all of you
to sign up to vote,
and I hope all of you did.
We called out also to the Labour Party
saying, listen, make a pitch to us.
We're going to
instruct our viewership
on how they should vote.
And we want you to tell us
why we should tell them
to vote for Labour.
You know, convince us
that Labour might at some point
be willing to build towards
being serious on wealth taxes.
You know,
I'm not demanding wealth taxes
now, but just give us some signal
that you could work towards them.
And in those three weeks
since we did that video,
we have been contacted by one
Labour MP, one backbench Labour MP,
which is great.
I won't name you, but thank you
very much for for calling out.
But yeah, one is unfortunately not
a great signal that Labour are going
to be serious on wealth taxes,
which means that I can now give you
my official recommendation
for who you should vote for this week.
If you want wealth taxes,
if you want to stop inequality
from growing, if you want to stop
living standards from falling,
I think this week
you need to vote for the Green Party.
And I've got my postal vote here,
which I'll be sending after this.
My postal, I'll be out
voting for the Green Party.
I think this is
it's pretty
obvious why I've done this.
We have one political party
in this country
which is really strongly
advocating for wealth taxes.
We have a government which really has
just really given me no indication
that they would ever be serious
even considering wealth taxes,
they've been quite reluctant
to talk to me about policy.
So it's with,
with a little bit of a heavy heart,
because I would have loved to have
a little bit more involvement.
But the fact is, if you want
wealth taxes in England in particular,
the only way that you can indicate
that to
the Labour Party
or the party in government
is to vote the Greens this week.
So I strongly advocate you to vote for
Greens,
and I will be voting
Greens this week on Thursday.
I should probably also mention,
because these elections
are not just in England, there are
elections in Scotland and in Wales.
And I know we do have people
watching from Scotland and Wales.
So for those who do not know or aren't
from the UK, in Scotland and Wales
we also have Scottish nationalists
and Welsh nationalists who are called
the SNP,
the Scottish Nationalist Party
in Scotland and Plaid Cymru in Wales.
Both of these parties
officially endorsed wealth taxes.
But I've asked
my Scotland expert called
Laurie
MacFarlane, who is a genuine
Scottish economist
who are the most passionate endorsers
of a wealth tax in Scotland,
and he says
it would probably only be the Greens.
The SNP have been talking
positively about wealth taxes,
which I really support, but the party
who are most enthusiastic
for wealth taxes in
Scotland is the Greens,
and the Welsh situation is similar
Plaid
Cymru have supported wealth taxes.
But the big standard bearers
for wealth taxes
in England and Wales
are the the Green Party.
So I think I would endorse the Greens
in Scotland and Wales as well.
But obviously if you have your reasons
to vote for the SNP or Plaid Cymru,
feel free to do that because they also
do support wealth taxes.
Now, I think the main reason why
it's important to do this is because,
as I've said,
we are almost certainly going to have
a leadership contest
within the Labour Party
for who will be the next prime
minister of this country
within the next two years.
It might be this year,
it might be very shortly
after the local elections,
or it could be next year.
But I think it is very likely
it will happen at some point.
And we don't know right now
who the next Prime Minister will be.
It will be a member of the Labour
Party, probably a Labour MP.
It could be Andy Burnham,
who is not a Labour MP,
but it could go a number of ways.
When you look at the betting market
for the next prime minister,
the betting market
really, really does not know.
You know, we have
you know, the runners and riders
are starting to step forward.
You know, the favorites are Angela
Rayner, Andy Burnham, Ed Miliband.
Wes Streeting.
But there is no clear favourite
and we really do not know
who it's going to be.
And the way
that this local election goes
this week
will have a really big bearing,
especially if the leadership campaign
is quite soon.
On who wins that leadership campaign,
who wins the next election,
in which direction the Labour Party,
which means our our country,
because they are our current
government goes.
And it will also have a big bearing on
where we sit on wealth taxes.
So if we come out of this election
and Labour do really, really well,
then that means that Keir Starmer may
well stay, which means
unfortunately,
we will probably not get wealth taxes.
If I'm totally honest,
I think for probably eight years
because I think Keir
Starmer will not do wealth taxes.
It seems pretty clear
that he doesn't want to do that.
I think if they keep him
till the next election,
they will lose and Reform will win.
So unfortunately,
as much as you know, you know,
I respect the Labour Party.
They are a powerful political party
and we do need their assistance
to some degree.
If Labour do well here, that's
no wealth taxes for eight years.
If Labour do badly,
then there is a question
of how will the new runners
and riders for new Prime minister
line themselves up?
And if we come out of this election
with Labour having done badly,
Reform will do well in this election
and the Greens will do
well in this election.
These things, like,
it is basically certain
Labour will lose a ton of seats,
Conservatives will lose
a ton of seats, and the Greens
and Reform will take a ton of seats.
If Labour do really badly
and the Greens do really
well and Reform don't do that
well, then...
It really begs the question,
to Labour, of
what are you going to do about this
big threat on your on your left,
which is Zack Polanski and the Greens.
And I would hope
if Labour are intelligent,
that they would recognize
the smartest thing to do
if they want to neutralize the threat
on the left of the Greens
would be to steal their most
popular policy, which is a wealth tax
and would be to talk to us,
and would be to
talk about how they can sensibly work
towards building, you know,
designing and planning a wealth tax
in such a way that it can work.
You know, talking to world leaders
on the planning of these things,
such as Gabriel Zucman
and his team of economists in France.
And I've got to be honest, like
I've been.
Well, I was going to say I've been
very disappointed with Labour so far.
But the truth is, I always predicted
that Labour would be very bad
and would be very unpopular.
But Labour have given us
nothing on wealth taxes so far.
This is probably
going to be our last chance
to convince Labour that they,
at the very least,
need to have a wealth tax candidate
in that leadership contest,
which may possibly happen
as soon as in the next few months.
And I'll be totally honest,
I think if we fail
at convincing Labour
to have at least one
wealth tax candidate
on the ballot in that leadership
contest, then Labour.
Will disappear in a relatively short
period of time.
I'm reminded of
what happened in the mid 2010s
which was the previous time
that Nigel Farage,
who is our far-right
leader, was really eating
into the conservative vote share
and Nigel Farage
was briefly disappeared
by the conservatives,
basically stealing Nigel Farage's
signature policy,
which was leaving the EU
and making it their signature policy.
And that basically destroyed
Nigel Farage for ten years.
And Nigel Farage was not
a political force for ten years.
He's only really coming back now.
If Labour want to
prevent themselves
from getting savaged by the Greens
at the next election, they need
to steal the world tax policy.
And I think
that is the only chance
of not getting destroyed.
There will be people watching
that will be saying, oh, you know,
we want Labour to be destroyed
because we're unhappy with them.
And I talk a bit a little bit about
that further later on in the video.
If you want wealth taxes,
in my opinion,
your best chance
of getting wealth taxes
within the next eight years is for
the Greens to do incredibly well now,
such that we can pressure Labour
to give us wealth taxes
after Keir Starmer is gone.
You're actually in this weird,
ironic situation where
almost the best way
for the Greens to win
the next election
is for the Greens to do badly now,
because then Labour
will not give us wealth taxes
and Labour will disappear,
which will do well for the Greens.
But this is my strong endorsement.
If the Greens do well today,
the Greens do well this week.
It's our last chance, really,
to get wealth taxes from Labour,
which is our last chance
to just save Labour
from themselves really And I'll talk
about what it means if Labour
don't do well and if Labour disappears
later on in the video.
But if the Greens do not
well and Reform do very well,
then it means that when that
Labour leadership contest happens,
it is much more likely to be won
by somebody on the right of the party.
You know, people talk about
Wes Streeting
as being on the right of the party,
who is less likely
to give us wealth taxes.
So basically, for me,
I think this local election is
basically the closest
you are going to get to a proxy vote
on wealth taxes
coming into the next election.
It will determine who the next prime
Minister is,
and it is our chance
to get wealth taxes in.
And if we don't do that,
then we will have a very weak Labour
and probably a Reform government.
So yeah, for me it has to be
the Greens at this local election.
But I think there is also a risk
and if I'm totally honest,
I can really,
really see this happening.
I think there is a real risk
that you guys will go out and vote
like you should,
and I'm going to vote as well.
We vote for the Greens.
The Greens do really, really
well in this local election.
Labour do really badly.
I think both those things,
those things will probably happen.
And somehow Labour failed
to recognize that this is related
to their wealth tax policy.
I've been speaking to some people in
Labour the last few weeks,
just honestly,
to try to understand why
they're not talking to me, because
it's honestly quite baffling to me.
And a lot of people that I've spoken
to, they don't think that the Greens
surge in popularity
and Labour's fall in popularity
is connected to wealth taxes at all.
So I think it is important
that if you do vote
for the Greens in this local election
because you want wealth taxes
and because you want lower inequality,
that whenever you can be,
you're vocal about it.
I think it's important
that Labour know the reason you're
voting against them
is because of their wealth tax policy.
And I think it's important
that the Greens know
that the reason you're voting for them
is their wealth tax policy,
because the Greens are surging
in popularity now.
And as they surge in popularity,
you know, lots and lots of people
will be lobbying them
to do lots and lots of things.
Up until now,
wealth taxes has been their,
I would say their flagship policy,
their most prominent policy.
There is a risk
that if the Greens don't realize
the reason you're voting for them
is because of wealth tax, is
they start to become distracted,
focus on other ideas
that will hurt their popularity,
and it will also take the pressure off
of Labour to do wealth taxes.
There is also a risk,
and I think this is really possible,
that Labour simply do not recognize
that a big reason
for the Greens surge in popularity
is because of wealth taxes.
So I think
if you can, I would like you
to sort of be quite vocal about this.
Don't sort of harass
or or heckler people in Labour,
but whenever you can,
if this means voting,
if this means writing to your MP,
or if this means
calling into talk shows
or just talking to your friends,
talking to your families,
making your own videos.
Be vocal whenever you can.
When you talk to anybody in public,
or if you can talk to the Labour
and say, listen,
we would love to vote for you,
but we cannot vote for you
while you are so aggressively
in opposition to the one
economic and tax policy
which could stop inequality
from rising, which is wealth taxes,
I think it's really important that
rather than this
becoming like a factional debate,
which is like Greens versus Labour,
that this is very,
very focused on policy,
because if we focus on policy,
then we can reach a situation,
I would like
to ideally reach a situation where
when we go into the next election,
we have both the Greens
and Labour aggressively supporting
wealth taxes, at least in principle.
And I think that that is obviously our
best chance of getting wealth taxes.
But it's also our best chance
of stopping Reform.
And whether or not you like Reform,
I think it has to be accepted.
If we don't get wealth taxes
and then we get a Reform government,
then that is eight years of no wealth
taxes because Reform, unfortunately,
I don't think will ever support
wealth tax as a policy.
So now I'm
going to get on to the point
which I mentioned
at the beginning of the video,
which is that I was quite heavily
advised not to do this video,
and some people would think that doing
this video is a bit of a risk.
And I'll explain to you why.
So, you know, I've been doing this
work on trying to support world taxes
since 2014, so nearly 12 years now.
And in that time
I've tried many, many things.
You know, I worked for a think
tank and I went back to university,
and now I'm obviously doing this
social media thing.
And, you know,
I've met a lot of people
who work in the field of trying
to convince political parties,
trying to convince government,
Conservatives, Labour on
how to do things.
And when I spoke to them
sort of a month ago, six weeks ago,
I was saying I was thinking of doing
this strategy where we tell everybody
to sign up to vote.
And we tell the government, listen,
we're going to push people to vote,
like, please give us a pitch.
And what people said to me was,
Labour won't give you a pitch,
they'll ignore you,
which will force you to endorse
the Greens.
And Labour can be
what I've been told.
And I don't know if this is true.
And if you're in Labour,
I'd love you to convince me otherwise.
I've been told that there are people
in Labour who don't like,
don't take being crossed very lightly,
and they don't take being spoken
against very lightly
And if you ever come out publicly
and say vote anyone
other than Labour, then nobody in
Labour will ever speak to you again.
And I'm aware
that this is potentially a risk.
But the truth is
we need to do something,
and I don't think
they are going to talk to us
unless we force them to talk to us.
If I'm totally, if I'm totally honest.
So I figured
it was worth the risk of of
trying to get something out of them,
because for so long
I've been trying to sort of play
a nicer game and have have failed
to get any real,
any real relationship.
But the real reason why
I was worried about doing this
video was not the sort of
these concerns that it would put me on
Labour's blacklist.
The real reason is because of
this, basically,
and I'm going to flash up here.
So I was looking the other day
at predictions for the next election.
And you know, I've done a video
on this about the betting markets.
But there's also another way
of predicting the next election,
which is to look at the polls.
And there's this group of people here,
electoral calculus, who make
a general election prediction
based on the current polling.
And I'm going to put
a link in the description,
but I'll also flash up here
what they're currently predicting
for the next election.
And you can see here
that the prediction
for the next election
at the moment is 266
seats for Reform, 107
for the Conservatives,
74 for the Greens in third
and everybody else under 70, Labour
coming in fifth.
And when you see that,
some of you who have been following
this channel for a long time
and see how how difficult
I found it to talk to Labour,
might take
a little bit of joy in that.
And might say,
oh, that's you know, that's
sort of just desserts for Labour for
being so bad.
And I
do think Labour have been really bad.
I think Labour have been really bad
on wealth taxes.
But the flip side of
that is if this really happens,
then what we will get is a Reform
Conservative.
Coalition government
and our chances of getting
wealth taxes or any significant
increase on taxes on the rich
under a Reform Conservative coalition
government are basically zero.
So if we continue the way
we are going,
then we will get in three years time
a Reform Conservative
coalition government.
And what that means is
we will not get wealth taxes
for eight years, because I think
it will be almost impossible
to get wealth taxes out of a Reform
Conservative coalition government.
And that's eight years
where inequality will increase
considerably and living
standards will fall a long way.
And I don't want that to happen.
And we need to be realistic about one
of the reasons why that is happening.
All right.
So we here in the UK we have
what is called a first past the post
voting system.
And maybe I'll do a video
explaining in more detail.
But just to summarize,
first past the post
voting system
aggressively punishes split votes.
And if you have a split vote on
the left, then the left, or do badly.
If you have a split vote on the right,
then the right will do badly.
One of the reasons why Labour won
a landslide in the last election
was because
we had a split vote on the right,
which was split
between the Conservatives and Reform,
and that is one of the reasons
why Labour were able to win
a big majority, despite
not actually getting that many votes.
So we have a voting system
which aggressively punishes division.
And when I sit here and advocate for
you guys out there voting Greens
this week, and I do think
that it is the strategic right
choice to vote Greens this week,
I have to recognize
and you have to recognize,
and we have to recognize
that when we advocate for that,
we are in many senses
advocating for a splitting of the
of the of the vote
on the left of this country.
We're in a situation
now where Labour are very unpopular.
The Greens are surging in popularity.
This website is predicting
the Greens will beat Labour
in the next election,
which I think, to be honest,
is very possible.
And as much as I would love, listen,
I've been really impressed
by the greens grabbing wealth taxes,
by Zack Polanski's work,
you know, I've met Zack
Polanski a number of times,
from what I've seen of him.
I like him.
But we have to accept
if we have a splintered vote
outside of Reform,
you know, and the Liberal Democrats
are getting 70 seats here as well,
and the SNP are getting 45 seats.
If the vote
outside of the right is splintered,
then that will probably mean
a Reform government.
And you know, I want this channel to
be like really welcoming to everybody.
So listen,
if you're out there
considering voting for Reform,
you know there's space for you
on this channel.
The reason I do not want a Reform
government
is because these guys,
the Reform Party, I am very confident
they will never support wealth taxes,
in my opinion, their economic policy
is primarily
about reducing taxes on the very rich.
So look,
the reason I'm hesitant in this video
is because as much as I'm really happy
to see like this
growing surge in green support
while they support world taxes,
I'm also aware that if we have this
like shattered,
divided political space
outside of Reform,
then Reform will win
the next election.
And I think when that happens,
I think the correct response from us
is to make sure as much as we can,
that we avoid factionalism and that we
avoid hatred amongst each other.
Now, listen, I've been sort of
floating around politics
for a long time in this country.
And, you know, I know and I've seen
there has been an awful lot of bad
blood between the center left,
which I guess is currently represented
by Labour, and the left,
by the Greens.
And I understand
why that bad blood is there.
And there will be some
who are supportive of the Greens
that will say, listen,
forget Labour, we can kill them
we can take them out.
The truth is, I think doing that
within the next three years,
the next election will
probably be in three years,
is going to be incredibly difficult.
You know, in the last couple of years,
the greens have played
a very good game
strategically and Labour have played
a very bad game strategically.
And if that continues,
a Labour wipeout is possible.
And if I start to think
that that is looking very likely,
I will inform you guys.
But Labour are going to change
leader.
Labour
are going to try to do a big rebrand.
If the Greens do really
well in this election,
maybe we can get something sensible
out of them on wealth taxes.
But we have to be realistic here.
Our chances of absolutely eliminating
the Labour Party
before the next election are slim.
So if we want to get wealth taxes,
we do need to be looking for ways
for how we can build
at least some level of understanding
between the different groups of people
in this country,
which includes like centrists
and people like Rory Stewart,
who I’m trying my best
not to be mean about, but centrists
like people who like Labour,
even ordinary people who might be
considering voting for Reform,
and people who are wanting to vote
for Liberal Democrats, Greens, SNP.
I think we need to be realistic
about what's happening here, right? So
when I go and say vote for the Greens,
this is not like Team Green.
This is not tie
your flag to the greens.
We are at
a pretty
dangerous moment here in the UK
and in the Western world.
You know, we can all look at
what's happening in the US.
under Trump, there is a global
resurgent and popular far right.
And in my opinion
the reason that they are so popular,
there's a number of reasons.
But the primary reason is because
they are the only political voice,
I would say, in this country
and in the world,
that has a clear message
that they communicate
about why living standards are falling
and how they're going to fix it.
And I don't think that
that message is true.
I think that we will see
and we will continue to see that
when they get into power,
they cut taxes on billionaires
and living standards fall.
I think Donald Trump is making
that as clear as anybody.
But until and unless
there is another political voice
in the room at the table
that has a clear message
about why living standards are falling
and how they're going to stop it,
then you will not be able
to see any political group
seriously challenge
the far right electorally.
So when I advocate for voting
for the Greens in this election,
I think it's really important
that you understand that
not as like a tribal vote
for the far left,
but as a way of trying to communicate
to everybody else
political centrists, even people
who might be voting for Reform
that there is an alternative
on the economy, which is the reason
living standards are falling,
is because of growing inequality.
And that can be resolved by increased
taxation of the very rich.
Tax wealth and not work.
So, you know,
I know that there may be people
in Labour who are very factional.
And I want to
make it really, really clear.
My preferred
outcome at the moment
for the next election is a Labour win.
I think that is our most
our best shot getting wealth taxes.
But I think we can only get
wealth taxes.
I think we can only get the Labour win
if Labour
give us something on wealth taxes.
I think if Labour don't move on wealth
taxes,
you know, save this in your diaries
because I'll be right.
If Labour don't move on wealth axes,
they will get f**king smashed.
Not just here in the locals,
but they will get smashed
in the general election.
And I do not want that to happen
because as happy as I am
of the excellent work
the Greens have done,
I struggle to see Labour
getting smashed in the next election,
producing any other outcome
other than a Reform win.
So look, get out there,
vote green, push wealth taxes.
Tell everybody you're doing it
because of wealth taxes.
And if you don't like the Greens,
you know,
if you want to vote for another party,
you know, be that Labour Lib Dems
Reform Conservatives,
join that party and campaign
aggressively within that party
for that party to adopt wealth taxes
in its policy manifesto.
We don't need them to say, look,
we're going to do wealth taxes today.
Just say we are going to get a team
of economists to research the design,
the feasibility, start working on it,
speak to the global experts on it,
and this is doable.
We had the message just this week
from somebody in the Conservative
Party that's like creating a group
in the Conservative Party,
making the conservative case
for wealth taxes.
I think the way that we win this,
it is policy over party.
And you aggressively support
the party
that gives you the best chance
of getting wealth taxes.
So that's where we are.
I think we're in a really weird spot
at the moment
where we if I'm totally honest,
I think we've played the blinder.
I think we've created this
massive space for wealth taxes and we
we should be having it in policy.
But the problem is Labour.
I think they're kind of stuck
in their Westminster bubble and
they're
they're struggling to move on it.
And I think we need to do everything
we can to shake them into sense
and make them realize
their only chance of not dying here
is to give us something
on wealth taxes.
And I know there will be
people watching that will be going mad
and saying, give up on Labour,
they've got no chance.
Come and help us with the Green Party.
And I understand that.
I understand
that, and, you know, best of luck
to Zack for the work that he's doing,
as soon as I look at this situation
and I honestly think our best chance
of getting wealth taxes
by the next election or within the
next eight years is with the Greens.
I will say that.
But I do think the fact is we've got
three years of Labour government now,
and I think we do need our
to do our best to slap them
into some semblance of sense.
So that's it.
Go out,
vote for the Greens. I'll be doing it.
But when you do vote for the Greens,
don't allow that to be a factional.
We hate Labour.
We hate everybody else thing.
If you want wealth taxes or
if you don't want a Reform government,
you need to be working on building
unity, building understanding
and more importantly,
building a central economic message.
And we are pitching strongly.
And I think it's becoming clearer
if you look around the world,
the only economic message that people
can unite around on the economy,
other than the far right message is
the problem is inequality.
The problem is billionaires.
It will be solved by taxing the rich.
All right. So thank you very much.
I'll be going to vote for
this afterwards.
I'll be going to France this week
on Sunday to meet with Gabriel Zucman,
who is, I believe, the global leader
on the design of wealth taxes,
a prestigious academic economist,
and also to promote the French
translation of my book,
which I don't have a copy,
but will maybe flash
you like a little photo of up here.
I’m really looking forward to it.
If you are worried about my either
pissing off Labour
or pissing off the greens,
which are both risks in the way
that I presented this video,
do support us to hire a lobbyist.
I think that's the thing that we need.
I think the big thing
that we've really missed
in the last couple of years is we've
been so successful on social media,
but somehow, like Labour
have managed to like, not notice.
And I think as much as I'd like
to point the finger at Labour and say,
what are you doing?
The fact is we have not been very good
at lobbying.
I've been incredibly busy.
Lobbying, charming
people, it's not my forte,
but I do think we need
a bit of professional support,
because I'll be totally honest
with you.
I'm worried because I think Labour,
unfortunately, are going to die
on their asses out there.
And there'll be people,
probably a lot of people
watching this video
that will be happy to see that.
And, you know, there might be
an element of schadenfreude from me
when I see how much they refuse
to speak to me.
But the truth is, I don't think Labour
collapsing is good.
I think if Labour collapse, it
significantly increases
the chance of a Reform government.
And if we get Reform government,
then that's eight years
of no wealth taxes.
So listen, stop hating each other.
Start supporting each other,
support our channel, support
the Patreon tax wealth not work.
And remember to vote this week.
Thank you
very much. See you next week.